<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.SMs.Coll.18</num>
                </titleproper>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2014-06-16T21:13-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc audience="internal" level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>James Brindley Diaries</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.SMs.Coll.18</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>0.25 Linear feet</extent>
                <extent>2 Volumes</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1794/1830" type="inclusive">1794-1830</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref7" label="Abstract">Two manuscript diaries of engineer James Brindley (1745-1820). Brindley, nephew of celebrated English canal engineer of the same name, worked on a number of canal projects in the United States, including the Potomac Canal in Maryland and the James River Canal in Virginia. The two diaries cover part of the time Brindley worked on the Susquehanna and Conewago Canal in 1794-1795, and Brindley's work on the Chesapeake and Delaware Canal in 1803.</abstract>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="local" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Brindley, James, 1745-1820</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <bioghist id="ref8">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>James Brindley (1745-1820), nephew of celebrated English canal engineer of the same name, worked on a number of canal projects in the United States, including the Potomac Canal in Maryland and the James River Canal in Virginia. After serving an apprenticeship with his uncle (James Brindley, "Father of English Canals"), the younger Brindley emigrated from England to the American Colonies in 1774 and settled in Wilmington, Delaware. Brindley took the Oath of Allegiance and Fidelity in 1778 and fought in the Revolutionary War on the side of the Americans. George Washington was acquainted with Brindley and noted his skill at canal building.</p>
            <p>Robert Morris financed the Conewago Canal, which facilitated access up and down the Susquehanna River and also to markets in Philadelphia, which were accessible from the River via the Philadelphia and Lancaster Turnpike in 1794. The Canal was completed in 1797. Brindley's diary covering the Conewago Canal dates from the period September 1794 to January 1795.</p>
            <p>The Chesapeake and Delaware Canal was first proposed by APS member Thomas Gilpin in the 1760s. A major effort was made in 1788 by among others Benjamin Franklin and Benjamin Rush to fund the Chesapeake and Delaware Canal, but it was not until 1802 that state governments provided funds. Work on the route did not start until 1803, digging only in 1804. Brindley's diary covers January to June 1803.</p>
            <p>Financial problems halted work for a time. It was not until the 1820s that state and federal govenments got the project going again. It was finished in 1829. With many improvements and some rerouting, the canal is still in valuable service today, carrying 40% of the cargo leaving Baltimore.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref1">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>Two manuscript diaries of engineer James Brindley (1745-1820). Brindley, nephew of celebrated English canal engineer of the same name, worked on a number of canal projects in the United States, including the Potomac Canal in Maryland and the James River Canal in Virginia. The two diaries cover part of the time Brindley worked on the Susquehanna and Conewago Canal, which went around Conewago Falls on the Susquehanna, and Brindley's work on the Chesapeake and Delaware Canal to link Chesapeake Bay and the Delaware River. Both these canals were of great interest to the APS.</p>
            <p>Brindley's diaries are full of engineering information, problems with financing and labor (pay could be infrequent and led to trouble), and many other details. There are drafts of letters to Willam Smith and Robert Morris, among others, in the Conewago diary, as well as two drawings.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <acqinfo id="ref2">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Accession M2012-01. Purchased from Michael Brown Rare Books, Philadelphia, with funds provided by Friends of the APS Library, 2/6/2012.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <prefercite id="ref3">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: James Brindley Diaries, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <processinfo id="ref6">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Processed by Michael Miller. June 2014</p>
        </processinfo>
        <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh">Canals.</subject>
            <subject source="local">Chesapeake and Delaware Canal</subject>
            <subject source="local">Conewago Canal</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Susquehanna River.</geogname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Technology -- History.</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref4" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Susquehanna and Conewago Canal Diary</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid13874002" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">1</container>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>1.0 Volume(s)</extent>
                        <extent>94 pages</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate normal="1794/1795" type="inclusive">1794-1795</unitdate>
                    <origination label="creator">
                        <persname rules="local" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Brindley, James, 1745-1820</persname>
                    </origination>
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref5" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Chesapeake and Delaware Canal Diary</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid13874001" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">2</container>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>1.0 Volume(s)</extent>
                        <extent>56 pages</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate normal="1803/1803">1803</unitdate>
                    <origination label="creator">
                        <persname rules="local" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Brindley, James, 1745-1820</persname>
                    </origination>
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
