<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.497.43.Z65-ead.xml">ziehm.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>Elsa Ziehm, Grammatik und Vokabular der Nahua-Sprache von San Pedro Jícora in Durango
                    <date type="span">1984-1986</date>
                    <num>Mss.497.43.Z65</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by rsc</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>2003</date>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T18:14-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>ENG</langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Grammatik und Vokabular der Nahua-Sprache von San Pedro Jícora in Durango</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.497.43.Z65</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="ger"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid118183" type="Volume" label="Bound materials">1</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>1.0 Volume(s)</extent>
                <extent>140 p.</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1984/1986" type="inclusive">1984-1986</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">The linguist and ethnomusicologist Else Ziehm became an expert in the San Pedro Jícora dialect of Nahuatl. As a result of anti-Semitism infecting the linguistics department at the University of Berlin in 1934, Ziehm switched to the Institut für Lautforschung and was awarded her doctorate for research on Romanian folk music in 1939. She began as an assistant curator at the Lautarchiv at the University, however the outbreak of the war only a few months later derailed her career. She returned to the field in the 1960s with the rediscovery of Konrad Theodor Preuss's Nahuatl manuscripts, editing them into a three volume edition that appeared between 1968 and 1976. Ziehm died in Berlin in 1993. 
                <lb/>Ziehm's "Grammatik und Vokabular der Nahua-Sprache von San Pedro Jicora in Durango" was announced by the Berlin publishing firm of Gebrüder Mann as a forthcoming title for 1980-1981, however the work was never finished. The typescript (140p.) with manuscript emendations, does not include the vocabulary.</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref1" label="General Physical Description note">1 vol., 140p.</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref11" label="Paging">LH-MV-B-10</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Ziehm, Elsa, 1911-1993</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>Relatively late in life, the linguist and ethnomusicologist Else Ziehm became an expert in the San Pedro Jícora dialect of Nahuatl. Born as Elsa Harmening on March 23, 1911, Ziehm was adopted by a Jewish family and took the family's surname Wertheim. As a result, she suffered from the virulent anti-Semitism infecting the linguistics department at the University of Berlin, causing her to leave in 1934 to study in the Institut für Lautforschung. After receiving her doctorate in 1939 for research on Romanian folk music, she began as an assistant curator at the Lautarchiv at the University, however the outbreak of the war only a few months later derailed her career.</p>
            <p>Having recently married the musician Hans-Jürgen Ziehm, Elsa left academia for 22 years to raise her children, resuming only with the rediscovery of Konrad Theodor Preuss's Nahuatl manuscripts which had somehow survived the war. She returned to doing field work and in 1985, lectured at the Freie Universität Berlin on Nahuatl. Her major publication was the three-volume 
                <title render="italic">Nahua-Texte aus San Pedro Jícora in Durango</title> (Berlin: Geb. Mann, 1968-1976), based on the texts collected by Preuss. Elsa Ziehm died in Berlin ob October 15, 1993.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref4">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>Elsa Ziehm's "Grammatik und Vokabular der Nahua-Sprache von San Pedro Jicora in Durango" was announced by the Berlin publishing firm of Gebrüder Mann as a forthcoming title for 1980-1981, however the work was never finished. The typescript (140p.) with manuscript emendations, does not include the vocabulary.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <prefercite id="ref6">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: Elsa Ziehm, Grammatik und Vokabular der Nahua-Sprache von San Pedro Jicora in Durango, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref7">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Gift of John Bierhorst, 2003 (accn. no. M2003-52).</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref8">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Catalogued by rsc, 2003.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref9">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>Other materials on the Nahuatl language are indexed in the online guide to the APS 
                <extref ns2:href=" http://www.amphilsoc.org/library/guides/indians/info/n.htm#nahua">American Indian Manuscripts</extref>.</p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <bibliography id="ref10">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <bibref>Bierhorst, John, "Elsa Ziehm, 1911-1993," 
                <title render="italic">Zeitschrift für Ethnologie</title> 121 (1996): 177-179.</bibref>
        </bibliography>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname source="ingest">Bierhorst, John</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Preuss, Konrad Theodor, 1869-1938</persname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Indians of Mexico</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Linguistics</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Nahuatl language</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
