<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.Ms.Coll.73-ead.xml"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.Ms.Coll.73</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T20:59-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>George Vaux papers, 1738-1985</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.Ms.Coll.73</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid2121" type="Box" label="Manuscripts">1-7</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>3.5 Linear feet</extent>
                <extent>Ca. 650 items</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1738/1985" type="inclusive">1738-1985</unitdate>
            <physdesc id="ref3" label="General Physical Description note">Ca. 650 items, 3.5 linear feet.</physdesc>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">The 18th century material includes the trans-Atlantic correspondence of James, Richard, and George V, along with domestic correspondence relating to family and business affairs. Several letters discuss Philadelphia during the British occupation, and seven discuss yellow fever in 1797-1798, with a particularly fine letter by Ann Warder discussing the epidemic of 1798. The participation of George Vaux VII in a Quaker mission to the Seneca Indians in 1803 is well documented. Later correspondence, almost all personal and familial in nature, documents the interest of George Vaux VIII in mineralogy, his travels abroad, and Vaux genealogy.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref6" label="Paging">LH-B-T7-1; LH-B-25-4 (OS)</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Correspondent (crp)">Vaux, George, VI</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Correspondent (crp)">Vaux, George, VII</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Vaux, George</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="naf" role="Correspondent (crp)">Warder , Ann Head, 1758-1829</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <acqinfo id="ref4">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Gift of George and Henry Vaux, 1992</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <bioghist id="ref1">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>The George Vaux Papers center on the family and business concerns of the surgeon, George Vaux V (1721-1803), and his lineal descedants, George Vaux VII, and George Vaux VIII (1832-1915). Many of the Vauxes, Quakers, were involved in charitable and reform activities, including anti-slavery, poor relief, and Indian missions. Other, related families represented in the collection are the Warders, Sansoms, Heads, Graffs, Morrises, Cressons, and Mayberrys.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <odd id="ref5">
            <head>African American History Note</head>
            <p>The collection may contain materials of interest relating to the family's involvement with the anti-slavery movement.</p>
        </odd>
        <odd id="ref7">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>The George Vaux Papers is a new and massive collection at the APS. The papers are focused on the business and financial interests of this very prominent Philadelphia family. What follows is a list of some of the more notable parts of this expansive collection: - Correspondence: There is a massive amount of correspondence, much of which is personal and familial in nature. Nonetheless, the letters often discuss politics, current affairs, and society. The earliest records date to 1701, although the great bulk are focused on the revolutionary era to the first quarter of the nineteenth century. - Almanacs, 1790-1870: The collection contains a large collection of small pocket almanacs from Philadelphia. Some of the earliest ones contain records of financial transactions and diaries. - Charles Thomson Correspondence: The collection has a series of letters from Charles Thomson, the Secretary of the Continental Congress. These letters are from the 1780s, after Thomson had largely retired from the political arena. - Legal and Estate Documents: This portion of the collection is extensive and difficult to summarize. The family owned a huge amount of property throughout the state. These papers contain deeds, information on rents, surveys of land, and other transactions. Moreover, the Vaux family had ties through marriage and friendship to other prominent families, and some of their estate business is included in this collection. Among the notable papers are documents pertaining to John and Sally Norris Dickinson's properties and the estates of the Emlens and the Sansoms. One document complements the Jane Aitken Collection, as it has an accounting of the Bible that she printed. - Travel Accounts: Most notably, George Vaux VII made a trip to "Indian Country" in 1802-1803. He wrote numerous letters home and kept a small and incomplete travel journal. - Philadelphia City Affairs: The Vaux were active in civic life. The collection contains information on city improvements, with specific letters and records relating to the water supply. The collection has letters that discuss building the Water Works, records of a Committee on the Sewers, and an agreement between the city and Peale's Museum. - Business Affairs: The record of the Vaux's diverse business interests is contained in this collection. In addition to their land holdings, the Vaux's were very active in internal improvements, with records from numerous navigation companies held in the collection. The Vaux's were also involved in mining and mineralogy, including Pennsylvania's oil lands, which is also reflected in the content of this collection. Finally, there are partial records of some prominent Philadelphia institutions, such as the Bank of Pennsylvania and the Philadelphia Contributorship. - Native American Documents - In addition to George Vaux's travels into Indian Country, there are extracts from Indian Treaties and some records of the Friendly Association in this collection.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <subject source="local">Abolition, emancipation, freedom</subject>
            <subject source="leah">African American</subject>
            <subject source="leah">American Revolution</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Antebellum Politics</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Business Records and Accounts</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Early National Politics</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Family Correspondence</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Genealogy.</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">General Correspondence</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Institutional Records</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Land speculation</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Legal Records</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Maps and Surveys</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Marriage and Family Life</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Mineralogy.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Native America</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Pennsylvania History</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Philadelphia History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Quakers -- Missions.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Seneca Indians</subject>
            <subject source="local">Slaves, slavery, slave trade</subject>
            <subject source="local">Social conditions, social advocacy, social reform</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Social Life and Custom</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Surveying and Maps</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Travel</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Yellow fever.</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
