<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.Ms.Coll.89</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T21:06-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc audience="internal" level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Susan Golla Papers</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.Ms.Coll.89</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid12636002" type="Box" label="Mixed materials">1-18</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>10.0 Linear feet</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1960/1990" type="inclusive">1960-1990</unitdate>
            <physdesc id="ref3" label="General Physical Description note">8 linear feet.</physdesc>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">Papers of an anthropological linguist.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref7" label="Paging">LH-SB-12-2</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Golla, Susan</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="ref5">
            <head>Scope and Content note</head>
            <p>The Golla Papers include research notes, subject files, field notes, copies of archival documents (photocopies; microfilm), audio recordings, 35 mm slides, and printed materials on Nootka Indians. ca. 9.5 linear feet of manuscripts, 40 recordings, 8 reels of microfilm.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <scopecontent id="ref6">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>Native American Images note : 334 color slides of potlatch ceremonies by Nootka (Nuu-chah-nulth) Indians of Port Alberni, British Columbia, 1976-1979. Images of singing, dancing, and bartering of wealth with gifts of food and goods at weddings and other spiritual festivals. Prints also display native dress, traditional musical instruments, and carving of a totem pole. Taken by Golla during her ethnological fieldwork on Vancouver Island.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist id="ref4">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>Upon graduating from George Washington University in 1971, Susan M. Golla (1948-1993) began her career as a research assistant to William Sturtevant at the Department of Anthropology of the Smithsonian Institution. In 1976, she received a research grant to study the Nootka Indians of Port Alberni, British Columbia. This work culminated in a doctoral dissertation, He has a name: history and social structure among the Indians of western Vancouver Island, from Columbia University in 1987. While teaching at such universities as Sarah Lawrence College, New York University, and City College of New York, she published articles on Nootka myths. At the time of her death, she was working on an annotated edition of selected Nootka texts, with detailed ethnographic and linguistic notes on texts by Edward Sapir. In her brief life, she made significant contributions to the study of Northwest Coast Native American societies.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <acqinfo id="ref2">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Gift of James M. Conmy, 1996. Susan Golla estate, bequest.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh">Indians of North America--British Columbia--Vancouver Island--Social life and customs</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Nootka Indians</subject>
            <subject source="local">Northwest Coast Indians</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Potlatch--British Columbia</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Slides.</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
