<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.973.2.B89r-ead.xml"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.973.2.B89a</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T18:27-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Fort Augusta (Pa.) account books, 1753-1765</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.973.2.B89a</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid1091" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">1-8</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>8.0 Volume(s)</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1753/1765" type="inclusive">1753-1765</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">These volumes include a record of personal expenses, 1753-1765, and entries made at Harris' Ferry, 1760, and at Fort Augusta, 1761-1763 (1 v.); ledgers, 1757-1764, with lists of soldiers with payments for wages (4 v.); a record of rations issued to Mr. Hunter's mess, Colonel Burd's company, and Mr. Graydon's mess, 1761-1763 (1 v.); day books, 1762-1763 (2 v.). All the volumes contain records of purchases of beef, venison, bread, corn, sugar, rum, butter, salt, etc.; records of payments for washing, tobacco, playing cards, tea, lemons, thread, combs; and records of purchase of medicines, shoes, clothing, etc.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref8" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-13 (973.2 B89r, -rs; 973.2 F77a, -d, -L; 973.2 H91r); LH-MV-E-16 (973.2 B89a, -m, -o, -r; 973.2 F77L)</physloc>
            <physdesc id="ref6" label="General Physical Description note">8 volumes.</physdesc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <corpname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Fort Augusta (Pa.).</corpname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd id="ref7">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>This collection relates to Fort Augusta, a Pennsylvania fort constructed and manned during the Seven Years’ War and Pontiac’s Rebellion. The fort was the only one the colony continued to support after peace in 1758 and was a central location for organizing a defense during Pontiac’s Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Summary(s) of Collection: The collection offers a near complete account of military matters at this very important fort in Pennsylvania’s defenses. The collection may be the most complete records of any Pennsylvania fort during Seven Years’ War. The data, which is primarily official account books of officers at the fort, includes names and data that may be of interest to genealogists and military and social historians. The information on supplies and goods also likely contain data that would be of interest to business historians and scholars interested in Native-white interactions.</p>
            <p>Fort Augusta Quartermaster Accounts (973.2 F77a; 973.2 F77d) This multi-volume portion of the collection covers the years 1757 to 1764. The accounts focus primarily on supplies, payments, purchases, and rations distributed.</p>
            <p>Alex Hunter’s Receipt Book – 1763-1764 (973.2 H91r) Compiled in the midst of Pontiac’s War, the receipt book includes rations distributed at fort and offers insight into daily workings of fort.</p>
            <p>Edward Shippen Docket Book (973.2 H91r) Appended to the back of Hunter’s Receipt Book are court records for 1764-1765 that are often civil cases involving debt.</p>
            <p>Major Burd’s Account and Receipt Books for 1756 and 1757 (973.2 B89r &amp; -rs) These records include payments owed and paid, including payments to individual soldiers for service.</p>
            <p>Major Burd’s Account Book – 1753-1763 (973.2 B89a) This small volume includes miscellaneous accounts, most from Fort Augusta but some from before. The records seem to be of personal rather than official transactions</p>
            <p>Major Burd’s Muster Rolls of Fort Augusta (973.2 B89m) Lists soldiers under Burd’s Command</p>
            <p>Orderly Book – 1757 (973.2 B89o) Contains the various movements and orders for the year at Ft Augusta</p>
            <p>Ledgers – 1760 (973.2 F77L) Three volumes. Detailed accounts for the year 1760, including payments made and purchases</p>
        </odd>
        <acqinfo id="ref5">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Received and accessioned, 1901 (54766-8). See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <custodhist id="ref3">
            <head>Custodial History note</head>
            <p>These volumes were probably originally among the Burd and Burd-Shippen papers.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Burd, James, 1726-1793</persname>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Account books.</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Fortification -- Pennsylvania.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Legal documents.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Military History</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Military Records</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Military supplies.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Native America</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Pennsylvania -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763 -- Equipment and supplies.</geogname>
            <subject source="leah">Pennsylvania History</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Seven Years' War</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763 -- Equipment and supplies.</geogname>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
