<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.K22-ead.xml">keating.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>William H. Keating Notebooks
                    <date type="span">1801-1839</date>
                    <num>Mss.B.K22</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by rsc</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>2004</date>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T19:36-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>ENG</langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>William H. Keating Notebooks</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.K22</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid13286001" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">1-4</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>4.0 Volume(s)</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1801/1839" type="inclusive">1801-1839</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">A mineralogist and chemist associated with the University of Pennsylvania (1822-1828), William H. Keating was a central figure in the scientific community in Philadelphia during the 1820s and 1830s. Active in the American Philosophical Society and Academy of Natural Sciences, and a founding member of the Franklin Institute, Keating was official geologist on Stephen Harriman Long's expedition to the Great Lakes in 1823 and spent three years in the late 1820s surveying the mineral resources of Mexico. 
                <lb/>The William H. Keating notebooks include three cash books (daybooks of cash expenditures, 1830-1839) and a book containing surveys of Keating lands in Potter County, most undertaken by Silas McCarty for William's father John Keating (1801-1818). The surveys associated with John Keating are an interesting record of land investment and speculation in the northern tier of Pennsylvania. William Keating's meticulous cash books provide a detailed record of his domestic expenses, philanthropic involvements (donations to the Catholic Church, the Prison Society), his reading (newspapers and books are listed individually), socializing (theatre tickets, Assembly fees), and a variety of miscellaneous expenditures ranging from purchase of a lithograph of Dugald Stewart to a table lamp from C. Cornelius. His accounts also include lists of servant's wages and wages for washerwomen.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref21" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-3</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Keating, William Hypolitus, 1799-1840 </persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd id="ref22">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>The William Keating collection consists of four volumes of records. Three volumes are his personal cash book, which records his financial transactions from 1830-1839. The fourth volume is a survey book. This volume contains detailed descriptions of land that the Keatings’ owned in Pennsylvania, likely purchased under or associated with the Holland Land Company. Keating’s surveys contain detailed descriptions of the land and area. At times, it reads like a travel narrative.</p>
        </odd>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref15">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>As an active member of the APS, Keating appears frequently as a correspondent in the APS Archives, and as a correspondent of 
                <extref ns2:actuate="onLoad" ns2:show="new" ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.Film.542-ead.xml">Charles Lucien Bonaparte (Film 542)</extref> and 
                <extref ns2:actuate="onLoad" ns2:show="new" ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.Film.628-ead.xml">John Torrey (Film 628)</extref>.</p>
            <p>
                <bibref>Keating, William H., 
                    <title render="italic">Account of Jeffersonite, a New Mineral Discovered at the Franklin Iron Works</title> (Philadelphia: Harding, 1822). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 549 P19 v.1, no.25.</bibref>
                <bibref>Keating, William H., 
                    <title render="italic">Considerations Upon the Art of Mining, to Which are Added, Reflections on its Actual State in Europe, and the Advantages Which Would Result from an Introduction of this Art Into the United States </title> (Philadelphia: Carey and Sons, 1821). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 622 K22.</bibref>
                <bibref>Keating, William H., 
                    <title render="italic">Narrative of an Expedition to the Source of St. Peter's River : Lake Winnepeek, Lake of the Woods, &amp;c., &amp;c. Performed in the year 1823</title> (Philadelphia: Carey and Lea, 1824). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 917.3 L85n.</bibref>
                <bibref>Keating, William H., 
                    <title render="italic">Syllabus of a Course of Mineralogy and Chemistry, as Applied to Agriculture and the Arts</title> (Philadelphia: s.n., 1822). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: Pam. v.1147, no.8.</bibref></p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <processinfo id="ref13">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Catalogued by rsc, 2004.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <acqinfo id="ref11">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Gift of Mark Willcox, February 2000 (accn. no. 2000-108ms).</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <prefercite id="ref9">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: William H. Keating Notebooks, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <scopecontent id="ref5">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The William H. Keating notebooks include three cash books (daybooks of cash expenditures, 1830-1839) and a book containing surveys of Keating lands in Potter County, most undertaken by Silas McCarty for William's father John Keating (1801-1818). The surveys associated with John Keating are an interesting record of land investment and speculation in the northern tier of Pennsylvania. William Keating's meticulous cash books provide a detailed record of his domestic expenses, philanthropic involvements (donations to the Catholic Church, the Prison Society), his reading (newspapers and books are listed individually), socializing (theatre tickets, Assembly fees), and a variety of miscellaneous expenditures ranging from purchase of a lithograph of Dugald Stewart to a table lamp from C. Cornelius. His accounts also include lists of servant's wages and wages for washerwomen. The final volume includes a loose pencil sketch of a pine tree.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>The mineralogist and chemist William Hypolitus Keating was born in Wilmington, Delaware, on August 11, 1799. The son of Baron John Keating, an Irishman by ancestry and former colonel in the French Army, William was educated at the University of Pennsylvania (AB, 1816) and studied mining in both France and Switzerland before joining the faculty at his alma mater in 1822. As the newly minted Professor of Chemistry and Mineralogy (1822-1828), he rapidly immersed himself in the city's vibrant community of mineralogists and chemists.</p>
            <p>A capable field geologist, Keating accompanied Stephen Harriman Long's second expedition in 1823 as official geologist and spent three years in mineralogical exploration in Mexico, beginning in 1827. His work with Long represented one of the first topographic and mineralogical surveys of the Great Lakes, for which he was given responsibility for compiling and publishing the results as 
                <title render="italic">Narrative of an Expedition to the Source of St. Peter's River : Lake Winnepeek, Lake of the Woods, &amp;c., &amp;c. Performed in the year 1823</title> (Philadelphia, 1824). Locally, he was as leading member of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia as well as one of the motive forces behind the establishment of the Franklin Institute in 1824. He was also an active member of the American Philosophical Society, serving both as Secretary (1823-1827, 1832) and Councillor (1831, 1836-1840), as well as a member of several committees.</p>
            <p>In addition to his scientific interests, Keating studied law and was engaged in a number of business enterprises. He died in London, England, on March 17, 1840, while negotiating a mortgage loan for the Philadelphia and Reading Railroad Co., of which he had been manager from 1835 to 1838.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname source="ingest">Keating, John</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">McCarty, Silas</persname>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Account books.</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Business Records and Accounts</genreform>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Daybooks.</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Finance, Personal</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Land and Speculation</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Maps and Surveys</genreform>
            <genreform source="ingest">Pencil works</genreform>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Potter County (Pa.)--Surveys</geogname>
            <subject source="leah">Surveying and Maps</subject>
            <genreform source="ingest">Surveys</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Surveys--Pennsylvania</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref16" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>William H. Keating Notebooks</unittitle>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>4 vols.</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate>1801-1839</unitdate>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref17" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Surveying notes, Potter County (Pa.)</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1 vol., 458p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1801/1818" type="inclusive">1801-1818</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Keating, John</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cash Book</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1 vol., ca.76p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1830/1833" type="inclusive">1830-1833</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Keating, John</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cash Book</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1 vol., ca.76p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1834/1836" type="inclusive">1834-1836</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Keating, John</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cash Book</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1 vol., ca.150p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1837/1839" type="inclusive">1837-1839</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Keating, John</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
