<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.506.7294.C33.1-ead.xml">cercle.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>Cercle des Philadelphes du Cap François Collection
                    <date type="span">1784-1787</date>
                    <num>Mss.506.7294.C33.1</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by rsc</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>2004</date>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T18:14-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>ENG</langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Cercle des Philadelphes du Cap François Collection</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.506.7294.C33.1</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="fre"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>0.25 Linear feet</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1784/1787" type="inclusive">1784-1787</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">Founded in Cap François, Saint Domingue (now Haiti) in August 1785, the Cercle des Philadelphes was one of the most prestigious colonial learned societies of the Ancien Regime. During its brief seven year existence, the Cercle pursued an agenda of promoting improvements in agriculture, manufactures, the arts and sciences, published five volumes of memoirs, and established correspondence with their peers in the American Philosophical Society and other learned societies. Their foreign membership included both Benjamin Franklin and Benjamin Rush. 
                <lb/>The Cercle des Philadelphes Collection is a small, but important assemblage of documents relating to French colonial science. Each of the documents is associated with Louis Narcisse Baudry de Lozières, the first president of the Cercle, including three certificates appointing him to office, and two important addresses. The first of these appears to be his opening remarks to the Cercle at its first public meeting on Aug. 15, 1784. The second is an early, but undated document outlining the organization of the Cercle and its aims.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref31" label="Paging">LH-MV-B-11; LH-SB-Black Case-15 (no.3, OS)</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <corpname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Cercle des Philadelphes du Cap François</corpname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd id="ref3">
            <head>General note</head>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Morel, p.236. Translated.</item>
                <item>Baudry de Lozières, Discours, Aug. 22, 1784.</item>
            </list>
        </odd>
        <bibliography id="ref18">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <bibref>Maurel, Blanche, "Une société de pensée à Saint-Domingue, le 'Cerle des Philadelphes' au Cap Français" 
                <title render="italic">Revue Française d'Histoire d'Outre-Mer</title> 48 (1962): 234-266. 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> 500 Pam. no.167.</bibref>
            <bibref>McClellan, James E., "L'historiographie d'une académie coloniale: le Cercle des Philadelphes (1784-1793)," 
                <title render="italic">Annales Historiques de la Révolution Franèaise</title> 3 (2000): 77-88.</bibref>
            <bibref>McClellan, James E., 
                <title render="italic">Colonialism and Science, Saint-Domingue in the Old Regime</title> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins, 1992). 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> 509.7294 M13c.</bibref>
        </bibliography>
        <odd id="ref32">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>This collection contains records of the Haitian science society called the Cercle des Philadelphes. The collection is small, containing only seven documents, and most of these are certificates. There are two addresses made by Louis Narcisse Baudry de Lozières, the president of the society, that might be of interest to historians of science. MOLE contains a detailed description and inventory of the collection.</p>
        </odd>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref17">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>
                <bibref>Arthaud, Charles, 
                    <title render="italic">Précis historique sur Monsieur le Chevalier Lefebvre-Deshayes, lu dans la séance publique du Cercle des Philadelphes, du Cap-François, le 20 juin 1786</title> (Cap François, 1786). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> Pam. 1101, 12.</bibref>
                <bibref>Cercle des Philadelphes, 
                    <title render="italic">Notice sur la séance publique du Cercle des Philadelphes, tenue le août, 1788</title> (Port au Prince, 1788). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> Pam. 1101, 15.</bibref>
                <bibref>Cercle des Philadelphes, 
                    <title render="italic">Statuts du Cercle des Philadelphes</title> (Cap François, 1785). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> Pam. 1101, 14.</bibref>
                <bibref>Cercle des Philadelphes, 
                    <title render="italic">Mémoires</title> (Port au Prince:Mozard, 1788). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> Pam. 1101, 15.</bibref>
                <bibref>Cercle des Philadelphes, 
                    <title render="italic">Prospectus du Cercle des Philadelphes, tenue le août, 1788</title> (Cap-François, 1786). 
                    <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> Pam. 1101, 15.</bibref></p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <processinfo id="ref15">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Recatalogued by rsc, 2004.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <acqinfo id="ref13">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Acquired from Wormser, 1953.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <prefercite id="ref11">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: Cercle des Philadelphes du Cap François Collection, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <scopecontent id="ref7">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The Cercle des Philadelphes Collection is a slender survival of one of the most prestigious colonial learned societies during the Ancien Regime, situated in Cap François, Saint Domingue (now Haiti). Each of the documents is associated with Louis Narcisse Baudry de Lozières, the first president of the Cercle, including three certificates appointing him to office, and two important addresses. The first of these addresses appears to be his opening remarks to the Cercle at its first public meeting on August 15, 1784. The second is an early, but undated document outlining the organization of the Cercle and its aims.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist id="ref5">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>In the 1780s, Cap François was one of the most cosmopolitan cities in the western hemisphere, the cultural capital of Saint Domingue (now Haiti). Blessed with a favorable climate and fueled by the extensive exploitation of slave labor, Saint Domingue emerged as the most profitable of all New World colonies during the last half of the eighteenth century, and during the summer 1784, a group of white residents of Cap François conceived of a plan to elevate the intellectual culture of their colony to match their financial success. Announcing that no society could exist "without the assistance of the sciences and arts," they created the Cercle des Philadelphes.</p>
            <p>Although formerly viewed as an outgrowth of freemasonry, the Cercle is now more generally seen as having been motivated by a complex mixture of both Royalist and patriotic impulses among the colonial elite. Devoted to "bonheur commun," they said, and motivated by "l'amour fraternal," the members of the Cercle applied themselves to study of the physical conditions, natural history, and medicine of the colony -- in essence, anything to promote the agriculture, manufactures, sciences, or arts.
                <ref target="ref3">
                    <emph render="super">1</emph></ref> The president, Louis Narcisse Baudry de Lozières, particularly emphasized the social benefits of "bonne intelligence" and the obligation for gentlemen to commit themselves to intellectual reciprocity and mutual assistance.
                <ref target="footnote2">
                    <emph>2</emph></ref>.</p>
            <p>From the outset, the Cercle was greeted warmly. It received official recognition and financial support from the crown as early as 1786, and on May 17, 1789, they were issued royal letters patent, the last group to receive this recognition prior to the Revolution. The Cercle also quickly forged official ties with Académie Royale des Sciences in Paris, with the American Philosophical Society, and with other provincial societies, academies, and museums, exchanging publications with the APS, for example, from at least 1788.</p>
            <p>Lead by Baudry de Lozières, an attorney, by the physician Charles Arthaud, and the writer M. F. E. Moreau de Saint Mé, the membership of the Cercle reached a peak of 160 in the late 1780s, drawing from a broad spectrum of the upper (white) classes in Saint Domingue. Physicians, judges and lawyers, planters and merchants, and public officials were all well represented, and the Cercle added a judiciously chosen slate of foreign members, including Benjamin Franklin and Benjamin Rush. It did not, however, long survive. Set back by the Revolution in France, the Cercle finally succumbed to the revolutionary violence in Saint Domingue in 1792.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname source="ingest">Arthaud, Charles</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Baudry de Lozières, Louis Narcisse, 1761-1841</persname>
            <subject source="leah">Beyond Early America</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Certificates.</genreform>
            <geogname source="LCNAF">France--Colonies--America</geogname>
            <geogname source="LCNAF">Haiti</geogname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Learned institutions and societies--Saint Domingue</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Miscellaneous</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Natural History</subject>
            <geogname source="LCNAF">Saint Domingue</geogname>
            <subject source="leah">Science and Technology</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref19" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Cercle des Philadelphes du Cap François Collection</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid6621" type="Box" label="Mixed materials">1</container>
                    <unitdate>1784-1787</unitdate>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Certificate authorizing Baudry as President</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid6624" type="Oversize" label="Mixed materials"></container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="17840815/17840815">1784 Aug. 15</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Baudry de Lozières, Louis Narcisse, 1761-1841</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discours prononcée dans la Societé des Philadelphes</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="17840822/17840822">1784 Aug. 22</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Baudry de Lozières, Louis Narcisse, 1761-1841</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref23">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Introductory address to the new society. Also signed by Charles Arthaud.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref24" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Certificate authorizing Baudry as President</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid6623" type="Oversize" label="Mixed materials"></container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="17850404/17850404">1785 Apr. 4</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Baudry de Lozières, Louis Narcisse, 1761-1841</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref25" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Certificate authorizing Baudry as Vice President</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid6622" type="Oversize" label="Mixed materials"></container>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3 lin. feet</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="17870226/17870226">1787 Feb. 26</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Baudry de Lozières, Louis Narcisse, 1761-1841</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref26" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Extrais des régistre du Cercle des Philadelphes</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="17870730/17870730">1787 July 30</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Baudry de Lozières, Louis Narcisse, 1761-1841</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Address</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Baudry de Lozières, Louis Narcisse, 1761-1841</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref29">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Prospects for the Society:</p>
                        <p/>
                        <p>formons une société de physique &amp; de Littérature et que note secret ne soit que celui du Génie ou de la science...</p>
                        <p>nos formules, au Lieu de ces minaudries enfantines qui elles memes ont renversé en grande partie le temple des maçons, doivent consister dans beaucoup de politesses, d'Egards et de bienséance parmi nous. Donnons le moins que nous pouvons à la matière. mettons de l'ordre dans tout ce que nous faisons: mais Evitons tour ce qui peut nous donner du Ridicule.</p>
                        <p>Que notre assemblée porte le nom de Museum Physico-Liiéraire de St. Domingue ou de Muéum Américan...</p>
                        <p>le Museum pourra aussi proposer des questions publiques que tous les colons pourront resondre [sic]..."</p>
                        <p/>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Wrappers for documents</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
