<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.630.943.B38-ead.xml">ruze.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>Ruze, C. F., Grundsätze der teutschen landwirthschaft vorgetragen von Johann Beckmann
                    <date type="span">ca.1810</date>
                    <num>Mss.630.943.B38</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by rsc</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>2003</date>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T18:22-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>ENG</langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Grundsätze der teutschen landwirthschaft vorgetragen von Johann Beckmann</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.630.943.B38</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="ger"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid115245" type="Volume" label="Bound materials">1</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>1.0 Volume(s)</extent>
                <extent>177 p.</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1810/1810">ca. 1810</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">One of the broadest scholarly minds at the University of Göttingen during the eighteenth century, Johann Beckmann helped establish the theoretical basis for scientific agriculture in Germany and pioneered a rational approach to technological innovation and government. 
                <lb/>The "Grundsätze der teutschen landwirthschaft" consists of exceptionally detailed notes kept by the otherwise unidentified C. F. Rüze on two well known works by the Göttingen scholar, Johann Beckmann. Organized page by page, apparently as Ruze worked his way through Beckmann's book, these are divided into two sections: "Einleitung in die teuchtschen Landwirthschaft überhaupt" (90p.), which are observations on 
                <title render="italic">Grunsätze der Teutschen Landwirtschaft</title>, and "Policey und Cameralwissenschaft" (87p.), which refers to Beckmann's 
                <title render="italic">Beyträge zur Oekonomie, Technologie, Polizey und Camaralwissenschaft</title>.</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref1" label="General Physical Description note">1 vol., 177p.</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref11" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-11</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Rüze, C. F.</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>One of the broadest scholarly minds at the University of Göttingen during the eighteenth century, Johann Beckmann helped establish the theoretical basis for scientific agriculture in Germany and pioneered a rational approach to technological innovation and government.</p>
            <p>Born at Hoya, Hanover, on June 4, 1739, Beckmann studied theology at Göttingen, but soon abandoned the ministry in favor of the natural sciences. At the invitation of Anton Friedrich Büsching, he accepted a position to teach natural history at the Lutheran academy in St. Petersburg, Russia, in 1763, however when Büsching left only two years later, Beckmann did as well. Returning to Germany by way of Scandinavia, where he met with Linnaeus, Beckmann was appointed Extraordinarius in Philosophy at his alma mater in 1763, transferring to the chair in rural economy seven years later.</p>
            <p>Rooted firmly in Enlightenment theories of rationality and systematic thought, Beckmann turned an intense focus on several discrete facets of applied knowledge. One of his earlier monographs, 
                <title render="italic">Grunsätze der Teutschen Landwirtschaft</title> (Göttingen, 1779-1791), went through numerous editions and was influential in introducing scientific principles to German agriculture. Perhaps more characteristic, however, was his encyclopedic five-volume 
                <title render="italic">Beiträge zur Geschichte der Erfindungen</title> (1786-1805), in which Beckmann traced the histories of dozens of major inventions used in the trades, the arts and sciences, and at home.</p>
            <p>Beckmann was equally well regarded by his contemporaries for his writings on political economy. His 
                <title render="italic">Beyträge zur Oekonomie, Technologie, Polizey und Camaralwissenschaft</title> (Göttingen, 1779-1791) exerted a strong influence on Cameralist governmental theory in late eighteenth century Germany, while his 
                <title render="italic">Anleitung zur Handlungswissenschaft</title> (Göttingen, 1789), 
                <title render="italic">Vorbereitung zur Warenkunde</title> (Göttingen, 1793), and 
                <title render="italic">Physikalisch-ökonomische Bibliothek</title>, 33 vols. (Göttingen, 1770-1778) were all widely distributed. Beckmann was elected to the Konigl. Societät der Wissenschaften at Göttingen in 1772. He died in Göttingen in 1811.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref4">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The "Grundsätze der teutschen landwirthschaft" consists of exceptionally detailed notes kept by the otherwise unidentified C. F. Rüze on two well known works by the Göttingen scholar, Johann Beckmann. Organized page by page, apparently as Ruze worked his way through Beckmann's book, these are divided into two sections: "Einleitung in die teuchtschen Landwirthschaft überhaupt" (90p.), which are observations on 
                <title render="italic">Grunsätze der Teutschen Landwirtschaft</title>, and "Policey und Cameralwissenschaft" (87p.), which refers to Beckmann's 
                <title render="italic">Beyträge zur Oekonomie, Technologie, Polizey und Camaralwissenschaft</title>.</p>
            <p>Written in old script German in a minute hand, the notes include occasional references to other works. The precise date of the volume is somewhat difficult to ascertain, however internal clues suggest an origin around 1810. The manuscript is written on a laid paper that appears to date from the earliest nineteenth century, and there is a citation in the essay on police to works of Beckmann's and Johann Christian Hellbach's that appeared in 1810.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <odd id="ref5">
            <head>General note</head>
            <p>"Rebacked in buckram; slipped in under old paper sides; old backbone and original label replaced, corners rebuilt." January 10, 1936, C. P. Rugh.</p>
        </odd>
        <prefercite id="ref7">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: C. F. Rüze, Grundsätze der teutschen landwirthschaft vorgetragen von Johann Beckmann, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref8">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Although the provenance of these notes is unclear, the manuscript is listed in J. Peter Lesley's 1863 printed catalog of the collections of the APS Library, and it is possible that the manuscript was here as much as fifty years earlier.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref9">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Recatalogued by rsc, 2003.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref10">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>
                <bibref>The Printed Materials Department houses an English translation of Beckmann's 
                    <title render="italic">A History of Inventions and Discoveries</title>, 3 vols. (London: J. Bell, 1797). 
                    <emph render="bold">608 B38h v.1-3</emph></bibref></p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <odd id="ref12">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname source="ingest">Beckmann, Johann, 1739-1811</persname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Agriculture--Germany</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Beyond Early America</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Government--Germany</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Police--Germany</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
