<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.G136.m-ead.xml">galton.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>Francis Galton Collection
                    <date type="span">1867-1909</date>
                    <num>Mss.B.G136.m</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by rsc</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>2004</date>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T19:27-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>ENG</langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Francis Galton Collection</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.G136.m</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>0.25 Linear feet</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1867/1909" type="inclusive">1867-1909</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">The polymath Francis Galton led a privileged and adventurous life, lending his talents to the development of statistical inference, scientific meteorology, psychology, and becoming one of the first to apply the evolutionary theories of his cousin Charles Darwin to human populations, founding the new fields of eugenics and biometrics. 
                <lb/>The Galton Collection is a miscellaneous assemblage of 15 letters and one photocopy written by Francis Galton to a variety of correspondents. These letters reflect Galton's research in meteorology, statistics, and, to a lesser degree, the heredity of intelligence.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref63" label="Paging">LH-MV-C-9</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <bibliography id="ref16">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <p>The APS has many of Galton's major published works, including:</p>
            <bibref>Galton, Francis. 
                <emph render="italic">Art of Travel</emph>, 4th ed. (London, 1867) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 910.2 G13a.4</bibref>
            <bibref>Galton, Francis. 
                <emph render="italic">English Men of Science</emph> (London, 1874) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 925 G13</bibref>
            <bibref>Galton, Francis. 
                <emph render="italic">Essays in Eugenics</emph> (London, 1909) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 575.104 G13e</bibref>
            <bibref>Galton, Francis. 
                <emph render="italic">Finger prints</emph> (London, 1892) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 573.6 G13f</bibref>
            <bibref>Galton, Francis. 
                <emph render="italic">Hereditary Genius</emph> (London, 1869) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 136.3 G1 (and other editions)</bibref>
            <bibref>Galton, Francis. 
                <emph render="italic">Inquiries into Human Faculty and its Development</emph> (London, 1883) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 575.1 G13</bibref>
            <bibref>Galton, Francis. 
                <emph render="italic">Memories of My Life</emph> (New York, 1909) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: B G136g</bibref>
            <bibref>Galton, Francis. 
                <emph render="italic">Natural Inheritance</emph> (London, 1889) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 575.1 G13n</bibref>
        </bibliography>
        <odd id="ref62">
            <head>Genetics Note</head>
            <p>This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.</p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colwidth="30%" colname="1"/>
                        <colspec colname="2"/>
                        <colspec colname="3"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry colname="1">Author</entry>
                                <entry colname="2">Format</entry>
                                <entry colname="3">Date</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left">Galton, Francis</entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left">Correspondence (16 items)</entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left">1867-1906</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table></p>
        </odd>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref15">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>Galton appears as a correspondent in several APS collections, including the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.M781-ead.xml">Moore Autograph Collection</extref> (3 items), the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.G784-ead.xml">John Edward Gray Papers</extref> (1 item), 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.P212-ead.xml">Paget Papers</extref> (4 items), the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.509.L56-ead.xml">Letters of Scientists Collection</extref> (1 item), the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.D27-ead.xml">Charles B. Davenport Papers</extref>, and the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/APS.Archives-ead.xml">APS Archives</extref> (1 item), and he appears in the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.H.S.Film.1-ead.xml">History of Science Microfilm 1 (Royal Society)</extref></p>
            <p>The major manuscript collections for Francis Galton appear at the University College London and the Royal Geographic Society.</p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <processinfo id="ref13">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Recatalogued by rsc, 2004.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <acqinfo id="ref11">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Acquired variously, 1967-1987 (accn. nos. 1967-1254ms, 1975-317ms, 1975-687.1ms, 1975-578f.ms, 1976-1327-1328ms, 1977-1298ms, 1977-603fms, 1978-1345ms, 1987-525ms).</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <prefercite id="ref9">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: Francis Galton Collection, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <scopecontent id="ref5">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The Galton Collection is a miscellaneous assemblage of 15 letters and one photocopy written by Francis Galton to a variety of correspondents. These letters reflect Galton's research in meteorology, statistics, and, to a lesser degree, the heredity of intelligence.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>The polymath Francis Galton (1822-1911) led a privileged and adventurous life, lending his talents to the development of statistical inference, scientific meteorology, psychology, and becoming one of the first to apply the evolutionary theories of his cousin Charles Darwin to human populations, founding the new fields of eugenics and biometrics.</p>
            <p>Born in Birmingham, England, on Feb. 16, 1822, Galton was still a boy when he was first gripped by a "passion for travel," touring eastern Europe and the Levant in the months before entering Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1840. At his parents' insistence -- and having already spent time studying at the General Hospital in Birmingham and at King's College, London -- Galton studied medicine at Cambridge. Yet medicine was not in his future. When his father died in 1844, the same year that he took a poll degree, Galton found himself liberated from the need to work, and almost immediately embarked upon a tour up the Nile as far as Khartoum and from there, to Syria. For five years, he dabbled in the sporting life, but after becoming thoroughly bored with leisure, he returned to travel. Approaching the Royal Geographic Society, Galton proposed leading an exploring expedition to Damaraland (present day Namibia), hoping to push from Walfish Bay inland to Lake Ngami, a lake which had been seen by Europeans only by David Livingstone. Galton failed in this attempt, but his account of that arduous journey, 
                <title render="italic">Tropical South Africa</title> (London, 1853), established him as an important explorer and earned him the gold medal of the Royal Geographic Society in 1853, the gold medal of the French Geographical Society in 1854, and election to the Royal Society in 1856.</p>
            <p>Despite having earned an enviable reputation as an explorer, Damaraland would be Galton's final expedition. Instead, he threw himself into a variety of scientific pursuits, and above all into quantitative inference. As an early experimental psychologist, he introduced the survey as a method for data collection, helped to demonstrate that different minds worked in different ways, promoted twin studies, and investigated the nature of memory and the senses. In meteorology, his work on atmospheric circulation (including coining the word "anticyclone") and his use of maps to show high pressure areas were both fundamental to the development of scientific weather forecasting. Although never as adept mathematically as he would have liked, Galton became a pioneer in the use of regression analysis during the 1870s and introduced the concept of statistical correlation in 1888. Using this approach, he helped to demonstrate that fingerprints were an index of personal identity, even persuading Scotland Yard to keep fingerprint records, and he stirred up a statistical controversy with a study that disproved the efficacy of prayer in healing. He also took on important administrative responsibilities: from 1868 to 1900 he served on the council of the Meteorological Office, and from 1863 to 1867 he was president of the British Association for the Advancement of Science.</p>
            <p>Galton's best known work, however, was inspired by his cousin. Within months of reading Darwin's 
                <title render="italic">Origin of Species</title>, Galton became a zealous convert and almost immediately set out to give statistical heft to the study of differences in human abilities. Struck by the tendency of genius to run in families (including his own), he amassed data on the heritability of intelligence, collecting the genealogies and obituaries of dozens of eminent persons and spinning the results into a succession of books. 
                <title render="italic">Hereditary genius: an enquiry into its laws and consequences</title> (1869) was followed by 
                <title render="italic">English men of science: their nature and nurture</title> (1874), 
                <title render="italic">Natural inheritance</title> (1889), 
                <title render="italic">Index to achievements of near kinsfolk of some of the Fellows of the Royal Society</title> (1904), and 
                <title render="italic">Noteworthy Families</title> (1906). In each of these, Galton argued that hereditary, not environment, was the key factor in explaining the distribution of intellectual (and other) talents in society. It was he who developed the catch phrase, "nature versus nurture," with the emphasis clearly on nature.</p>
            <p>As early as 1865, Galton sought to turn his understanding of heredity actively to improve the human race, an idea he popularized in 
                <title render="italic">Inquiries into Human Faculty and its Development</title> (1883), the book in which he introduced the term eugenics. He intended this neologism to refer to the scientific effort to improve the human race through selective breeding of the best elements of society and discouragement of breeding of the worst. In his autobiography, Galton wrote that the aims of eugenics were simple and clear, and were rooted in biology.</p>
            <p/>
            <p/>
            <p>Infirm during the last several years of his life, Galton died of acute bronchitis on Jan. 17, 1911. His wife Louisa Jane Butler, whom he married in August 1853, died in 1897, and he had no children. The bulk of his estate was left to the University College London to endow the laboratory of eugenics and to establish a chair in eugenics, of which the statistician Karl Pearson was the first tenant.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Clarke, Hyde, 1815-1895</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Frere, Henry Bartle Edward, 1815-1884</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Jebb, Henry Gladwyn</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Miller, W. J. C. (William John Clarke)</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Proctor, Annie</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Ravenstein, Ernest, 1834-1913</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Strachey, Richard, Sir, 1817-1908</persname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Eugenics</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Heredity</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Meteorology</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref17" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Francis Galton Collection</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid55001" type="Box" label="Mixed materials">1</container>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>0.25 lin. feet</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate normal="1867/1909" type="inclusive">1867-1909</unitdate>
                </did>
                <controlaccess>
                    <subject source="local">Eugenics</subject>
                    <subject source="local">Evolution</subject>
                    <subject source="local">Human genetics</subject>
                    <subject source="local">Population genetics</subject>
                    <subject source="local">Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics</subject>
                </controlaccess>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Richard Strachey</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 4p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1867/1867">1867 Nov. 6</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref20">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Requesting clarification on Strachey's paper on meteorology in the Proceedings of the Royal Society.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Henry Gladwyn Jebb</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 4p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1870/1870">1870 Aug. 20</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref23">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Request for information on the Jebb family. "It seems to me the two desiderata in the present state of the 'heredity' discussions are (1) Families with a large number of able men in consecutive generations. (2) an estimate, or a statement of possible, of the number in that family who were not included in the first category."</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref24" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to William John Clarke Miller</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 3p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1873/1873">1873 April 8</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref26">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Requests Miller's assistance with forwarding a mathematical (statistical) problem to Mr. Carr.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Hyde Clarke</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 3p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1873/1873">1873 June 19</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref29">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Bartle Frere's plans to establish a "black settlement under British protection" as head to a railway to the gold fields.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to "Dear Bart"</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1873/1873">1873 Dec. 20</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref31" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Ernest George Ravenstein</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 3p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1877/1877">1877 June 22</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref33">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Regarding map of African explorations and African plans.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref34" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Richard Strachey</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 4p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1878/1878">1878 May 24</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref36">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Developments in meteorological research.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref37" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Richard Strachey</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 2p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1880/1880">1880 Apr. 9</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref39">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Meteorological research: seeking a synonym for "depression" and suggests "bathic."</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref40" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Moncure Daniel Conway</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS Cy, 3p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1882/1882">1882 Apr. 24</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref42">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Sends an admission ticket to Darwin's funeral. "I can hardly express to you how deeply I feel Charles Darwin's death owing more to him 
                            <emph render="italic">spiritually</emph> than to any other man..."</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <originalsloc id="ref44">
                        <head>Existence and Location of Originals note</head>
                        <p>From original at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.</p>
                    </originalsloc>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref45" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Richard Strachey</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 2p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1882/1882">1882 May 18</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref47">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Has set Curtis to work reading the number of day degrees.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref48" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to 
                            <title render="italic">Nature</title>. Editor</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 3p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1893/1893">1893 Jan. 18</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref50">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Regarding his paper to "show how easy it is to express pictures, place &amp; such illustrations in outlines, as are from time to time wanted to illustrate telegraphic intelligence, by a 
                            <emph render="italic">paragraph of numerals</emph>."</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref51" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Annie Procter</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 2p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1898/1898">1898 Jan. 27</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref52" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Annie Procter</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 3p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1898/1898">1898 Feb. 23</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref54">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Regarding trip home from France.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref55" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Annie Procter</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 4p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1899/1899">1899 April 14</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref57">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Traveling in Spain. Loss of old friends. Enjoyed the bull fights in Seville.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref58" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to Lady Strachey</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>ALS, 2p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1909/1909">1909 June 28</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref60">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Would like to call, but is too infirm.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref61" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>to John Simon</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>Postcard, 1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="naf">Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911 </persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
