<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.R735w-ead.xml"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.B.R735w</num>
                </titleproper>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T19:56-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Will of George Ross</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.R735w</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>1.0 Item(s)</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate>July 10, 1779</unitdate>
            <physloc id="ref4" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-6</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="local" source="local">Ross, George, 1730-1779 </persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="ref1">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>D.S. 4p. Proved and probated July 16, 1779, S: Th. Bond, Saml Morris, et al.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <acqinfo id="ref2">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Deposited by the Register of Wills Office, Phila; Aug. 1955.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <accessrestrict id="ref3">
            <head>Conditions Governing Access note</head>
            <p>Restricted, cf. terms of use, Legal folder.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <odd id="ref5">
            <head>General note</head>
            <p>FILM 895.7 FRAME</p>
        </odd>
        <bioghist id="ref6">
            <head>Biographical/Historical Note</head>
            <p>George Ross (1730-1779) was a lawyer, a member of the Pennsylvania Provincial Assembly, vice-president of the Pennsylvania Constitutional Convention, a member of the First and Second Continental Congresses and a signer of the Declaration of Independence. Ross was born in New Castle, Delaware, the son of the Anglican rector of Immanuel Church Rev. George Ross and his wife Catherine Van Gezel. He received a sound private classical education at home. He read the Law in his brother John’s law firm and was admitted to the bar in Philadelphia at the age of twenty. Afterward, he moved to Lancaster, Pennsylvania to set up a law practice in 1751. Also, in 1751 he married Ann Lawler, with whom he had three children. He served as the king’s prosecutor from 1756-1768, and as an assemblyman in the Pennsylvania Provincial Assembly from 1768-1775. Although originally a moderate in the controversy engendered by the new colonial trade regulations and taxes after the French and Indian War, the events of the Boston Tea Party and passage of the Coercive Acts pushed Ross into the Whig camp of those seeking American independence from Great Britain. Ross was elected to the Pennsylvania Provincial Conference on July 15, 1774 and then to the First Continental Congress. In addition to his congressional service, he was appointed to the Pennsylvania Committee of Public Safety, as well as the Lancaster County Committee of Observation. As vice-president of the Pennsylvania Constitutional Convention of 1776, Ross helped to draft the Pennsylvania Declaration of Rights, but ended up opposing the Pennsylvania constitution of 1776, which he considered too radical. Another major source of conflict for Ross was the Pennsylvania Test Acts, from which he and other Republicans recoiled. As part of the Continental Congress, Ross participated in the debates on July 2-4, 1776 to amend Thomas Jefferson’s draft of the Declaration of Independence. Elected to the Second Continental Congress, Ross signed the Declaration of Independence on August 2, 1776. Ross was appointed judge of the Admiralty Court of Pennsylvania in March 1779, and presided over the important case of Olmsted et al. v. Rittenhouse’s Executors, which raised serious questions regarding the prerogatives of a state government and its courts in conflict with federal authorities. Ross died of gout in Lancaster, Pennsylvania in 1779.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <odd id="ref7">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>The will of George Ross contains detailed information on this prominent Pennsylvanians estate at the time of his death. It discusses his land holdings in Lancaster and elsewhere and some of his personal belongings.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <genreform source="leah">Legal Records</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Miscellaneous</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Pennsylvania History</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
