<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.Film.283,513,74</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney. Revised by Iren Snavely (NEH, 2010)</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T20:14-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>William Maclure letters; 1796-1848</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.Film.283,513,74</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid1825" type="Reel" label="Microform">1-11</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>11.0 Microfilm reel(s)</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1796/1848" type="inclusive">1796-1848</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">This collection includes letters to Maclure, journals of travel in Europe and America, notes and essays. Also included are manuscripts, transcripts, and notes relating to Maclure.</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref14" label="General Physical Description note">11 microfilm reels.</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref16" label="Paging">LH-RR-Media Rm-1</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Maclure, William, 1763-1840</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <acqinfo id="ref13">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Received from Working Men's Institute, New Harmony, Indiana, 1950; Letters to Benjamin Silliman received from Yale University Library, 1955.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <odd id="ref9">
            <head>General note</head>
            <p>Some of these letters were published in Arthur E. Bector, "Education and Reform at New Harmony..." (Indiana Historical Society Publications, 1948).</p>
        </odd>
        <bioghist id="ref7">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>William Maclure (1763-1840, APS 1799) was a merchant and geologist. In addition to serving as president of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia (1817-1840), he introduced Pestalozzian methods of education in the United States, and also founded a school in Robert Owen's utopian community in New Harmony, Indiana.</p>
            <p>Maclure was born in Ayr, Scotland on October 27, 1763 to David and Ann Maclure and educated by private tutors. He traveled to the United States in 1782 to establish “mercantile arrangements,” and returned to London as a partner in the commercial firm of Miller, Hart and Company, soon amassing a fortune. As a merchant, he traveled between Europe and America, but also spent several years traveling around the European continent, including Scandinavia and Russia. He observed geological features and studied with geologists in several countries. In Paris, for example, he met Count Volney, who discussed American geology with him. Maclure returned to the United States in 1796, and examined its geologic formations, as he crossed “the dividing lines of the principal formations in 15 or 20 different places.” In 1809 he published a report with a colored map, entitled “Observations on the Geology of the United States, Explanatory of a Geological Map” in the 
                <emph render="italic">Transactions</emph> of the American Philosophical Society.</p>
            <p>In 1815 Maclure traveled to France, where he met the artist-naturalist Charles Alexandre Lesueur. He persuaded Lesueur to return to America with him as his personal cartographer-naturalist. During the winter of 1815-1816, they investigated the geology and natural history of the West Indies, then moved the U.S. mainland, crossing the Allegheny Mountains in order to collect specimens and to revise Maclure’s geologic map. Late the following year, from December 1817 to April 1818, Maclure organized an expedition of Georgia and Spanish Florida, that included Lesueur and the Americans Thomas Say, Titian Peale and George Ord.</p>
            <p>From 1820-1824 Maclure lived on and developed an estate he purchased in Spain. This property was confiscated in 1824, and Maclure returned to the United States to join the Scottish utopian socialist Robert Owen in the establishment of the New Harmony community in Indiana. Maclure invested $82,000 in the project. Several years later in 1827 he first visited Mexico, and later moved there to live out the remaining years of his life.</p>
            <p>Maclure’s best known work is the 
                <emph render="italic">Observations on the Geology of the United States</emph>, which was the “first connected account” (originally) written in English. He expanded and revised the original as a separate volume in 1817. In this work he divided the country into geologic areas of “primitive rocks,” “transition rocks,” “floetz and secondary rocks” and “alluvial rocks.” Maclure’s 1818 “Essay on the Formation of Rocks ...” is also important for its explanation of his terminology and his theory on the origin of rocks. Finally, his brief 1838 paper entitled “Genealogy of the Earth-Geological Observations” has been described as the most “philosophical” of his geological writings. In this work he adopted the theory of Lamarckian evolution, and explained his belief in organic and inorganic development through a gradual series of “minute changes,” rather than catastrophes or large jumps. He rejected the aqueous theory of the origin of primitive rocks, but was uncertain about their actual origin, thinking perhaps they might be diverse in origin.</p>
            <p>Maclure was not only a great geological observer and maker of important maps, he provided significant support for scientists and scientific organizations. He was one of the founders of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, and its president from 1817 until his death in 1840.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <originalsloc id="ref5">
            <head>Existence and Location of Originals note</head>
            <p>Originals of the letters to Benjamin Silliman in Yale University Library, New Haven, Connecticut.</p>
        </originalsloc>
        <originalsloc id="ref3">
            <head>Existence and Location of Originals note</head>
            <p>Originals of part of the collection in Working Men's Institute, New Harmony, Indiana.</p>
        </originalsloc>
        <odd id="ref15">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>This is a microfilm of an early American collection that may be of interest to researchers at the APS and may complement an original manuscript collection at the APS.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Amphlett,  W. (William), fl., 1796-1819</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Burrough, Marmaduke, ca. 1798-1844</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Erving, George William, 1769-1850</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Fretageot, Marie Duclos, 1783-1833</persname>
            <persname source="naf">Lesueur, Charles Alexandre, 1778-1846</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Maclure, Alexander</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Owen, Robert Dale, 1801-1877</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Owen, Robert, 1771-1858</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Rich, O.,  (Obadiah), 1777-1850</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Say, Lucy Way Sistaire, 1801-1886</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Say, Thomas, 1787-1834</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Speakman, John</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Wright, Frances, 1795-1852</persname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Collective settlements.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Education -- United States.</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Europe -- Description and travel.</geogname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Geology.</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Journals (notebooks).</genreform>
            <geogname source="lcsh">New Harmony (Ind.)</geogname>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Spain -- History -- 19th century.</geogname>
            <geogname source="lcsh">United States -- Description and travel.</geogname>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
