<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.Sh92r-ead.xml"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.B.Sh92</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T20:00-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>George Harrison Shull papers, 1874-1955</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.Sh92</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid1598" type="Box" label="Manuscripts">1-12</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>6.0 Linear feet</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1874/1955" type="inclusive">1874-1955</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">This collection consists of materials relating to Shull's work commissioned by the Carnegie Institution of Washington to collaborate with their grantee, Luther Burbank, with the aim of analyzing Burbank's data on plant breeding and hybridization and preparing it for publication in suitable scientific journals. Shull visited Burbank's plant-breeding farm in California eight times between 1906 and 1910. There are files for each plant genus involved in Burbank's work. These files contain notes, calculations, clippings from newspapers or periodicals, and an unpublished manuscript of Shull's final report to the Carnegie Institution. There is also a report by Edwin C. MacDowell, which gives background information about the collection.</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref12" label="General Physical Description note">6 linear feet.</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref18" label="Paging">LH-B-23-11; LH-MV-B-1 (B Sh92r); LH-MV-E-6 (B Sh92.1)</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <acqinfo id="ref11">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Presented by the Carnegie Institution of Washington and accessioned, 07/27/1965 (1965 1476ms). 2 notebooks presented by Herbert P. Riley and accessioned, 03/08/1966 (1966 334ms). 40 letters to HPR presented by Herbert P. Riley and accessioned, 1969 (1969 320ms).</p>
            <p></p>
        </acqinfo>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref17">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>There are 90 letters to or from G. H. Shull in the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.B585-ead.xml">Blakeslee Papers (B B585)</extref>, 561 in the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.D27-ead.xml">Davenport Papers (B D27)</extref>, 36 in the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.D394-ead.xml">Demerec Papers (B D394)</extref>, 72 in the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.J44-ead.xml">Jennings Papers (B J44)</extref>, and 44 in the 
                <extref ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.Ms.Coll.5-ead.xml">Stern Papers (Ms. Coll. 5)</extref>.</p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>George Harrison Shull was a botanist. He was a botanical investigator at the Carnegie Institution of Washington from 1904 to 1915 and taught botany and genetics at Princeton University from 1915 to 1942.</p>
            <p>G. H. Shull worked on hereditary variation in many different plants during his career: the evening primrose (
                <emph render="italic">Oenothera</emph>), the shepherd's purse (
                <emph render="italic">Bursa</emph>), Indian corn (
                <emph render="italic">Zea</emph>), bean (
                <emph render="italic">Phaseolus</emph>), pink (
                <emph render="italic">Lychnis</emph>), foxglove (
                <emph render="italic">Digitalis</emph>), sunflower (
                <emph render="italic">Helianthus</emph>), tomato (
                <emph render="italic">Lycopelricon</emph>), poppy (
                <emph render="italic">Papaver</emph>), potato (
                <emph render="italic">Solanum</emph>), and tobacco (
                <emph render="italic">Nicotiana</emph>). He is chiefly noted, however, for one major achievement that laid the foundation for the development of hybrid corn and the other hybrids responsible in the latter part of the twentieth century for the "Green Revolution." This was probably the single most important agricultural advance of the century. It has been estimated that during World War II, when hybrid corn was first cultivated, it increased corn yields in the United States by 20 per cent -- a gain of 1.8 billion bushels worth $2 billion dollars, enough to pay for the Manhattan Project, and also enabling the United States to ship vast quantities of food abroad after the war, and so to prevent famine and pestilence.</p>
            <p>Although many others were involved in the development of hybrid corn, Shull's contribution was the basic one. In breeding begun in 1905 at Cold Spring Harbor, he applied the principles of Mendelian heredity to analyze the inheritance of quantitative characters in corn (maize), especially the number of rows of kernels per ear. He self-pollinated the corn in order to produce a number of pure, inbred lines that differed in the average number of rows. These lines, as inbreeding continued, declined in vigor and productivity. When, however, they were crossed, the hybrids were not only extremely uniform but also highly vigorous and productive. They were definitely superior to the original open-pollinated strains with which Shull had started his work. Shull's papers of 1908 and 1909 describing this series of experiments in detail laid the basis for hybrid corn breeding with its higher yields, greater uniformity, more exact specializations to fit particular climates and soils, and desirable chemical content and nutritive qualities. Paul C. Mangelsdorf has said: "Certainly it was one of the most remarkable achievements of our time in the field of applied biology. Shull's idea of producing and maintaining otherwise useless inbred strains of maize solely for the purpose of utilizing the increased vigor and uniformity resulting from their hybridization was revolutionary as a method of corn breeding. It is still the basic principle which underlies almost the entire hybrid corn enterprise." In December, 1905, the Carnegie Institution of Washington selected G. H. Shull as the geneticist to work with the famed plant breeder Luther Burbank, to whom the Carnegie Institution had made a handsome grant of funds, in order to prepare "a scientific account of the ways, means, methods, and results of Mr. Burbank's work... " (President Woodward's first annual report, in the 
                <emph render="italic">Yearbook</emph> of 1905). Shull was to begin in March, 1906, was to return to Cold Spring Harbor to carry on his own work from June through September, and then return to Santa Rosa to collaborate with Luther Burbank as long as necessary.</p>
            <p>In July of 1906 Shull made a preliminary report to the Carnegie Institution of Washington. The unpublished manuscript of this report, a remarkably perceptive document commenting fully on Burbank's methods and results, and expressing also the great difficulties experienced by the young geneticist in trying to work with the opinionated elder plant breeder, remained unpublished in the Shull Papers, until unearthed and published by Bentley Glass (
                <emph render="italic">Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society</emph>, 124: 133-153. 1980). As the sequel showed, nothing much ever came of the project, although Shull spent a number of additional months at Santa Rosa in the effort to complete his work. It dragged on until 1914, when Shull finally used the outbreak of World War I as an excuse to terminate the project. The Shull Papers, in addition to the manuscript of the 1906 report, contain newspaper and magazine clippings and handwritten notes by Shull, arranged genus by genus, all relating to Burbank's extensive collections of wild species and varieties of plants and his hybridizations.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <odd id="ref16">
            <head>Genetics Note</head>
            <p>This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.</p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colwidth="30%" colname="1"/>
                        <colspec colname="2"/>
                        <colspec colname="3"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry colname="1">Author</entry>
                                <entry colname="2">Format</entry>
                                <entry colname="3">Date</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left">
                                    <ref target="ref14">Riley, Herbert P.</ref></entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left">Correspondence (32 items)</entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left">1932-1952</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table></p>
        </odd>
        <processinfo id="ref25">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Index incomplete.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926</persname>
            <corpname rules="aacr" source="naf">Carnegie Institution of Washington.</corpname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">MacDowell, E. Carleton,  (Edwin Carleton), 1887-1973</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Riley, Herbert Parkes, 1904-</persname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Botany.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Flowers.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Genetics.</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Notebooks.</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Plant breeding--California</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Plant genetics.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Plants.</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Reports.</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref13" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Selected Inventory from Genetics Subject Guide</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref14" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Riley, Herbert P.</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>32.0 Item(s)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1932-1952</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref15" label="General Physical Description note">Correspondence ( 32 items )</physdesc>
                    </did>
                    <controlaccess>
                        <subject source="local">Biographical and personal data</subject>
                        <subject source="local">Educational matters -- Textbooks</subject>
                        <subject source="local">Evolution</subject>
                        <subject source="local">Genetics -- Nomenclature</subject>
                        <subject source="local">Genetics of plants</subject>
                        <subject source="local">History of biology, especially genetics</subject>
                        <subject source="local">International Congress of Genetics</subject>
                        <subject source="local">Princeton University</subject>
                        <subject source="local">Publication</subject>
                        <subject source="local">Teaching</subject>
                        <subject source="local">World War II -- Impact on science</subject>
                        <subject source="local">Zea (maize) genetics</subject>
                    </controlaccess>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oenothera notebook</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B Sh92.1</unitid>
                        <container id="cid13287008" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">1</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref20" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Herbert [Parkes] and Agnes Riley;</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>Aug. 20, 1941</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref22">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Princeton, N.J., A.L.S.: Geo. H. Shull and family. 8p. Botanical and genetic news. Difficulty in having the APS publish his study. Personal news. Presented by Dr. Riley; Sept. 13,1968. Interfiled with other Shull papers.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref23" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Herbert [P. Riley];</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>Nov. 18, 1948</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref24">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Princeton, N.J., A.L.S. 4p. Sorry he lost his building by fire but hopes he can rebuild it better. Genetics and botany. His herbarium and the loss of one at Princeton. Presented by Dr. Riley; Sept. 13, 1968. Interfiled with other Shull papers.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
