<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.B.P31.17-19</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T19:52-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc audience="internal" level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Peale's Museum (Philadelphia, Pa.) minutes; accounts, 1820-1845</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.P31.17-19</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid1488" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">1-5</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>5.0 Volume(s)</extent>
                <extent>5 volumes, 295 p. </extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1820/1845" type="inclusive">1820-1845</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">This collection includes minutes, 1821-1836 (2 v.), recording actions of the trustees of Peale's Museum (John Bacon, Pierce Butler, Reuben Haines, Joseph Parker Norris, Robert Patterson, Robert Maskell Patterson, Coleman Sellers, George Escol Sellers, and others), including exhibits, purchases of specimens, appointment of personnel, financial statements, etc. There is also an account book, 1820-1824 (1 v.), being a record of daily income of the museum, and stock books, 1827-1836, 1841 (2 v.), consisting of stubs of certificates of stock sold to subscribers to the museum, with a quantity of unused certificates.</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref15" label="General Physical Description note">5 volumes, 295 p.</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref18" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-4</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <corpname rules="aacr" source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Peale's Museum (Philadelphia, Pa.).</corpname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <acqinfo id="ref14">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Presented by Charles Coleman Sellers and accessioned, 1945 (85097-8). Photocopy of typed transcriptions presented by the Barra Foundation and accessioned, 04/02/1976 (1976 794ms).</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <altformavail id="ref8">
            <head>Existence and Location of Copies note</head>
            <p>There are also photocopied transcriptions of minutes housed in the Smithsonian Institution Archives (1821-1827) and in the Historical Society of Pennsylvania (1841-1845). Not copied are Rough Minutes, 1828-1835 (at the APS), and Rough Minutes, 1841-1845 (at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania). The materials from the Smithsonian Institution Archives are also available on microfilm (Film 1331) and in a bound photocopy (1 v.).</p>
        </altformavail>
        <bioghist id="ref6">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>Peale's Museum was established by Charles Willson Peale in 1784. It was public rather than private in character and was governed initially by a Society of Visitors. The museum was moved to the Hall of the American Philosophical Society in 1794 and in 1802 by act of the Pennsylvania Assembly it ws granted the free use of the State House (Independence Hall) recently vacated by the legislature. It was subsequently incorporated as the Philadelphia Museum Company under the direction of a board of trustees. The museum met with financial difficulties in th 1830s, and the collections were sold in parts, the portraits being the last to be sold in 1854.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <originalsloc id="ref4">
            <head>Existence and Location of Originals note</head>
            <p>Originals of the transcribed copies are located in the American Philosophical Society Library,the Historical Society of Pennsylvania,and the Smithsonian Institution Archives.</p>
        </originalsloc>
        <odd id="ref16">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>These five volumes contain documents relating to the incorporation and management of Charles Wilson Peale’s Philadelphia Museum Company. The records begin in 1821, when Peale was still alive and overseeing the operations, pause until 1828, then pick back up and end in 1836.</p>
            <p>The collection also houses two volumes of stock certificates for the years 1827-1836 and 1841, with many of the later issues signed by Titian Peale, and a record of income for 1820-1824.</p>
            <p>The minutes are especially detailed for the period 1828-35. The minutes show a board that was interested in and cognizant of their need to create a profitable organization. The minutes show how the museum continued to be a business endeavor throughout the nineteenth century, even after Peale had left active management.</p>
            <p>The volume that contains the income for Peale’s Museum records income by day and is often divided into daily and nightly returns. There is also room for notes, which are sometimes used to explain why attendance is down. For instance, election days are noted and in 1820, it is noted that “alarm of fever abating.”</p>
            <p>A collection of silhouettes/profiles done by Peale are included within these call numbers.</p>
        </odd>
        <odd id="ref17">
            <head>Administrative Note</head>
            <p>This record is superseded by, and included in, B P31. It was marked “internal only” in Dec., 2010 and is being kept in the case that it is needed for future administrative needs.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Bacon, John, 1738-1820</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Butler, Pierce, 1744-1822</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Haines, Reuben, 1786-1831</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Norris, Joseph P.,  (Joseph Parker), d. 1863</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Patterson, , Robert M.,  (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Patterson, Robert, 1743-1824</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Peale, Charles Willson, 1741-1827</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Peale, Rubens, 1784-1865</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Sellers, Coleman,b. 1827.</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Sellers, George Escol</persname>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Account books.</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Business and Skilled Trades</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Business Records and Accounts</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Literature, Arts, and Culture</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Minutes.</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Museums -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Philadelphia History</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Stock certificates.</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
