<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.R89t-ead.xml"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.B.R89t</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T19:58-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Travels through life:or an account of sundry incidents and events in the life of Benjamin Rush...written for the use of his children, [1800]</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.R89t</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid1569" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">1-8</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>8.0 Volume(s)</extent>
                <extent>8 volumes, 494 p. </extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1800/1800">Circa 1800</unitdate>
            <physdesc id="ref12" label="General Physical Description note">8 volumes, 494 p.</physdesc>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">This autobiography relates Rush's experiences in college and medical school; his meetings with notable doctors; his life in Scotland, England, and France; his medical views; the military and politics during the Revolutionary War; and brief sketches of personalities of that period.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref15" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-6; LH-MV-E-15</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="ref13">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>Includes lengthy comparison of French and Indian manners, illustrating civilization degenerating into savagery.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref11">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>The ninth surviving volume of this autobiography is in the Library Company of Philadelphia, 1314 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA 19107.</p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <acqinfo id="ref7">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Purchased from Biddle ($7000.00)and accessioned, 10/12/1943.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <odd id="ref5">
            <head>General note</head>
            <p>All nine volumes of this autobiography have been published; see George W. Corner, ed., "The Autobiography of Benjamin Rush: His Travels through Life, together with his Commonplace Book for 1789-1813," 
                <emph render="italic">American Philosophical Society Memoirs</emph> 25 (1948).</p>
        </odd>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>Benjamin Rush was a physician, patriot, and humanitarian. He graduated from the College of New Jersey (Princeton), 1760, and from the University of Edinburgh, 1768. He was a member of the staff at the Pennsylvania Hospital and was a professor at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <odd id="ref14">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>Benjamin Rush’s Travels Through Life is his multi-volume autobiography. This manuscript copy is in his own hand and takes up eight volumes of notebooks. The APS also has another manuscript copy of the work that was written by someone other than Rush, likely in preparation for its publication. Rush wrote the autobiography for his children. The APS published portions of the diary, but segments have not been published. Notations suggest that portions that would be “offensive to surviving relatives” be omitted from publication. Other sections were crossed out but are readable and contain pertinent information. This is especially true on the section where Rush records his thoughts on prominent individuals from the American Revolution.</p>
            <p>The diary covers Rush’s life up to 1800 in intricate details. Rush describes his involvement in the American Revolution, especially his work in fomenting opposition to British policies and his interactions with many prominent revolutionaries. He provides many fascinating, lively, and important anecdotes from the events leading up to Independence, many of which were private meetings and dinners. Among those he records was witnessing Thomas Paine pen Common Sense. In terms of the personal, Rush describes his studies, his travels, his thoughts, including various dreams that he had and how they affected him, and his personal life, including courting.</p>
            <p>Aside from the personal, the journals also provide insight into Philadelphia culture and society with Rush describing what it was like to visit houses and tend to patients. He also contains short biographical sketches of “those gentlemen who were most conspicuous for their talents and virtues.”</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Fothergill, John, 1712-1780</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790</persname>
            <subject source="leah">American Revolution</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Autobiographies.</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Autobiography</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Diaries</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Early National Politics</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">England -- Social life and customs -- 18th century.</geogname>
            <subject source="ingest">Epidemics--United States</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">France -- Social life and customs -- 18th century.</geogname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Indians of North America</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Marriage and Family Life</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Medicine</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Medicine.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Philadelphia History</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Scotland -- Social life and customs -- 18th century.</geogname>
            <subject source="leah">Social Life and Custom</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Personal histories.</geogname>
            <geogname source="lcsh">United States -- Politics and government -- 1775-1783 -- Anecdotes, facetiae, satire, etc.</geogname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Yellow fever -- United States.</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
