<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.SMs.Coll.8-ead.xml"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.SMs.Coll.8</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Adam Najarian</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T21:21-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Keugh, Lieutenant William, Report of British Officer to His Majesty from Camp at German Town 28th of Setptemr. 1777</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.SMs.Coll.8</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>1.0 Volume(s)</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1777/1777">1777 September 28- October 7</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">Lieutenant William Keugh (b. 1732) was an Irish-born officer in the British army during the French and Indian War and the American Revolutionary War. Serving as Adjutant for the 44th Regiment of Foot, Keugh wrote Report of British Officer to His Majesty from Camp at German Town 28th of Setptemr. 1777, which chronicles the Philadelphia campaign of 1777, including descriptions of the Battles of Brandywine, Paoli and Germantown.</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref4" label="General Physical Description note">1 volume.</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref10" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-17</physloc>
        </did>
        <bioghist id="ref2">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>Born in Ireland in 1732, William Keugh was an officer in the British army during the French and Indian War, as well as the American Revolutionary War. He served as the adjutant of the 44th Regiment of Foot from July 9, 1760 to July 10, 1782, eventually earning promotion from ensign to lieutenant on November 28, 1771, then to captain-lieutenant on November 1, 1779.</p>
            <p>While a member of the 44th Foot, Keugh served in Canada, Ireland and America. He participated in the conquest of Canada during the French and Indian War, as well as actions against Boston, New York and Philadelphia during the American Revolution. Some of the engagements he participated in include the Battle of Long Island (1776), the Battle of Brandywine (1777) and the Battle of Monmouth (1778). The 44th Foot was sent to Canada in 1782, where Keugh retired on September 26, 1782, after twenty-two years in the service.</p>
            <p>Work Referenced: McGuire, Thomas J. The Philadelphia Campaign: Germantown and the Roads to Valley Forge, Volume 2 (Mechanicsburg, PA: Stackpole Books, 2007), 288.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <acqinfo id="ref5">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Gift of Robert L. McNeil, Jr., 2006. (McNeil number M249.)</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <prefercite id="ref7">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Lieutenant William Keugh Report on the Battle of Germantown, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <processinfo id="ref8">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Processed by Adam Najarian, 2010.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <scopecontent id="ref9">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The account, entitled Report of British Officer to His Majesty from Camp at German Town 28th of Setptemr. 1777, is a report by Lieutenant William Keugh, Adjutant of His Majesty’s 44th Regiment of Foot to General of the Army James Abercrombie, his commanding officer. Keugh was identified as the author of the account by historian and author Thomas J. McGuire. The account describes the Philadelphia campaign of the American Revolution from the Battle of Brandywine to the Battle of Germantown, including the Paoli Massacre. Due to Keugh’s position as Adjutant, or staff officer, the account includes information regarding the movements of supply trains and artillery, not just the conduct of the battle. Also mentioned are the British landings at Head of Elk, Maryland, as well as a partial list of British casualties during the campaign. Though the account is dated September 28, 1777, Keugh references in the text that it was written over a period of several days, concluding on October 7, 1777, just three days after the conclusion of the Battle of Germantown. The account was a gift of Robert L. McNeil, Jr., in 2006.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <odd id="ref11">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>This collection contains an official account of the British Army's actions in the Philadelphia-area during the American Revolution. It complements SMS Coll 7 and SMS Coll 9. Recorded by British Army officer Lieutenant William Keugh, the after action report is extensive and detailed.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Clinton, Henry, Sir, 1738?-1795</persname>
            <persname source="naf">Grey, Charles, 1729-1807</persname>
            <persname source="naf">Howe, William Howe, 5th Viscount, 1729-1814</persname>
            <persname rules="dacs" source="local">Knyphausen, Wilhelm zu Innhausen und, Reichsfreiherr, 1716–1800</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Washington, George, 1732-1799</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Wayne, Anthony, 1745-1796</persname>
            <subject source="leah">American Revolution</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Brandywine, Battle of, 1777</subject>
            <subject source="local">British Landing at Head of Elk, Maryland, 1777</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Germantown, Battle of, 1777</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Military History</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Military Records</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Official Government Documents and Records</genreform>
            <subject source="local">Paoli Massacre, 1777</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Philadelphia History</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
