<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.P31.50-ead.xml"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.B.P31.50</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T19:52-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc audience="internal" level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Sellers family papers, 1675-1928 (inclusive)</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.P31.50</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid1517" type="Box" label="Manuscripts">1-4</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>3.0 Linear feet</extent>
                <extent>Ca. 1500 items.</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1675/1928" type="inclusive">1675-1928</unitdate>
            <physdesc id="ref10" label="General Physical Description note">Circa 1500 items.</physdesc>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">Correspondence among members of the Sellers and Peale families, with special emphasis on the Sellerses, ca. 1789-1860. Topics include such family matters as travel, household expenses, children, deaths and funerals, social and cultural life in Philadelphia, with some doggerel verses. There are also letters regarding patents, inventions, and the Sellers' businesses. Principal correspondents include: Coleman Sellers (1781-1834) and his wife Sophonisba Angusciola Peale (1786-1859), and their children Anna (1824-1908), Coleman (1827-1907), and George Escol (1808-1899); also Ann Sellers (b. 1785), Hannah Sellers and her husband Peter Hill (d. 1857); Mrs. Cornelia Wells Sellers (1831-1909); Mrs. Elizabeth Coleman Sellers (1751-1832); and the following members of the Peale family: Charles Willson, Raphaelle, Rembrandt,Franklin, Charles Linnaeus, Rubens, and Titian Ramsay Peale.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref34" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-5</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <famname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Sellers family.</famname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <acqinfo id="ref9">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Presented by Charles Coleman Sellers, 1945, 1956. Volumes 5-7 purchased from Charles Coleman Sellers and accessioned, 1945; volumes, 1-4 donated by Charles Coleman Sellers and accessioned, 09/--/1954 (1954 474-480ms).</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <odd id="ref3">
            <head>General note</head>
            <p>The Sellers family is described in Charles Coleman Sellers, "Sellers Papers in the Peale-Sellers Collection," American Philosophical Society Proceedings 95(1951):262-265.</p>
        </odd>
        <otherfindaid id="ref15">
            <head>Other Finding Aids note</head>
            <p>Only maps and scanned images are noted.</p>
        </otherfindaid>
        <odd id="ref31">
            <head>African American History Note</head>
            <p>There is at least one item in this collection which may be of interest to students of African American history:</p>
            <p>Carre, John Thomas. Letter to Charles Willson Peale. Circa 1792. Describes Carre's escape from the slave uprising in Saint Domingue.</p>
        </odd>
        <odd id="ref32">
            <head>Administrative Note</head>
            <p>This record is superseded by, and included in, B P31. It was marked “internal only” in Dec., 2010 and is being kept in the case that it is needed for future administrative needs.</p>
        </odd>
        <odd id="ref33">
            <head>Early American History Not</head>
            <p>This large collection has a wide array of documents relating to early American history. Content includes revolutionary war documents, travel journals, manuscript essays, and extensive correspondence. What follows below is a description of some of its most notable content.</p>
            <p>Among the earliest documents are letters and other forms that chronicle the American Revolution, primarily as it was experienced in Philadelphia. Among the items is a pass for Nathan Sellers, a petition from Charles Wilson Peale for a memorial for the war dead, committee reports from the Pennsylvania Assembly, and letters.</p>
            <p>The collection also has surveys and documents that relate to the Sellers families interests in internal improvements and engineering.</p>
            <p>As this is a large collection of family papers, family, business, education, and various other social matters are often discussed, providing a portrait of this prominent Philadelphia family and the society and culture in which they lived. The collection has, for instance, the love letters passed between Nathan Sellers and his future wife Elizabeth. Nathan had been disowned by the Darby Friends’ Meeting for his service in the militia, so his courtship of Elizabeth had to be covert. The letters were thus written using pseudonyms. There is also a lot of correspondence between the De Peyster family of New York and the Peales, especially to Charles Wilson.</p>
            <p>Among the more notable items that are not directly related to the wider Sellers-Peale families is an essay by Thomas Jefferson on fossil bones and various attempts at poetry by members of the family, sometimes written as part of courtship (some come packaged with lockets of hair). Also of note are: a couple of the letters that touch upon the family’s experience during the War of 1812, with a particularly detailed letter from Rembrandt Peale to Reuben describing the situation in Baltimore; a travel journal kept by Ann Sellers on a trip up the Hudson River in 1815; a few brief personal diaries kept by various members of the family during the nineteenth century; and a letter describing the mob that formed in Philadelphia in 1819 to witness a balloon. Art was an important part of this family.</p>
            <p>While much of the artwork of the Peales is contained in their individual collections, the Sellers-Peale family papers have a letter from Charles Wilson Peale to his son Raphael in 1820 describing the arrangement of the color palette and a note from Rembrandt Peale in 1845 describing his Court of Death.</p>
            <p>Members of the Sellers family moved west, to Ohio, in the nineteenth century. Various correspondence and other documents provide insight into their life and experience there, especially in Cincinnati.</p>
            <p>There is a detailed inventory of all the documents.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Hill, Hannah Sellers</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Hill, Peter, d. 1857</persname>
            <persname source="naf">Latrobe, Benjamin Henry, 1764-1820</persname>
            <famname source="ingest">Peale family.</famname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Peale, Charles Linnaeus, 1794-1832</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Peale, Charles Willson, 1741-1827</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Peale, Franklin,1795-1870.</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Peale, Raphaelle, 1774-1825</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Peale, Rubens, 1784-1865</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Peale, Sophonisba Angusciola,1786-1859.</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Sellers, Ann,b. 1785.</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Sellers, Anna,1824-1908.</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Sellers, Coleman,1781-1834.</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Sellers, Coleman,b. 1827.</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Sellers, Elizabeth Coleman, 1751-1832</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Sellers, George Escol</persname>
            <subject source="local">Abolition, emancipation, freedom</subject>
            <subject source="leah">American Revolution</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Artists -- United States.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Education</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Family Correspondence</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">General Correspondence</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Inventions.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Inventors -- United States.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Land and Speculation</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Legal Records</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Literature</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Literature, Arts, and Culture</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Maps and Surveys</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">Marriage and Family Life</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Official Government Documents and Records</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Patents.</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Pennsylvania -- Industries.</geogname>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Social life and customs.</geogname>
            <subject source="leah">Philadelphia History</subject>
            <subject source="local">Race, race relations, racism</subject>
            <subject source="local">Slaves, slavery, slave trade</subject>
            <subject source="local">Social conditions, social advocacy, social reform</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Social Life and Custom</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Surveying and Maps</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Technology -- United States.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Travel</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Travel Narratives and Journals</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc/>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
