<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.917.7.M19-ead.xml">PUBLIC "-//American Philosophical Society LIBRARY//TEXT(US::PAAV::917.7 M19:: Thomas L. McKenny Sketches of a Tour to the Lakes)//EN" "mckenny.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>Thomas Loraine McKenney, Sketches of a Tour to the Lakes
                    <date type="span">1826</date>
                    <num>Mss.917.7.M19</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by rsc</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>2002</date>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T18:25-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>ENG</langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Sketches of a Tour to the Lakes</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.917.7.M19</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>3.0 Volume(s)</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1826/1826">1826</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">The 
                <title render="italic">Sketches of a Tour of the Lakes, of the character &amp; customs of the Chippeway Indians &amp; of incidents connected with the treaty of Fond du Lac... to which is super added a vocabulary of the Algic, or Chippeway language...</title> is a record of a journey undertaken by Thomas L. McKenney and Lewis Cass, from Washington, D.C., to Fond du Lac, Wisc., to negotiate a treaty with the Chippewa and other Indians. McKenney, the Superindenant of Indian Affairs, includes an account of travel on the Great Lakes, and more memorably, a description of the "character" and customs of the Chippewa Indians, an account of the treaty of Fond du Lac, and a vocabulary of the Algic or Chippewa language. The manuscript, a fair copy of the original sent to a London publisher, is illustrated throughout with watercolor sketches of scenes and persons. It was originally published in Baltimore in 1827.</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref1" label="General Physical Description note">3 vols.; 0.5 linear feet</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref43" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-12</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">McKenney, Thomas Loraine,1785-1859.</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>The son of devout Quakers from the Eastern Shore of Maryland, Thomas Loraine McKenney was appointed by James Madison as Superintendent of the Indian Trade in 1816. A strident opponent of the emerging Jacksonian Democracy, McKenney's years in office were marked by partisan strife and improfitability. His zealous support for John C. Calhoun's bid for the presidency in 1824 earned him the wrath of Congress, and a special investigation of his Office. McKenney was fully exonerated, and after Calhoun removed himself from the race in return for the vice presidency, McKenney was rewarded for his loyalty with an appointment as the nation's first Superintendent of Indian Affairs.</p>
            <p>In both his Superintendencies, McKenney allied himself with the policies of his predecessors in the Washington and Adams administrations, aiming to "civilize" the Indians rather than merely exterminate them. He was the prime supporter of the Indian Civilization Act of 1819, which provided funds for Indian education, but he was also supported the Removal Act of 1830 with its devastating consequences for the Indians of the eastern states. McKenney later justified his support for the act by arguing that removal was more humane than the alternative. Regardless of his intentions, shortly after the act went into effect in the fall of 1830 he was dismissed from office by Andrew Jackson. Although he remained active in anti-Democratic politics, he was never again appointed to office, and spent the last decade of his life in obscurity, living in Brooklyn. He died on February 20, 1859.</p>
            <p>Kenney's long-term reputation is based in large part, as he predicted it would, on the Office (later Bureau) of Indian Affairs that he helped establish, but above all on his two major proto-ethnographic works: 
                <title render="italic">Sketches of a Tour of the Lakes</title> (1827) and the 
                <title render="italic">History of the Indian Tribes of North America</title> (1844). His later 
                <title render="italic">Memoirs, Official and Personal</title> (1846) were written in defensive mode, justifying his actions while in office against his many detractors.</p>
            <p>The 
                <title render="italic">Sketches</title> is an engaging account of a treaty negotiation in 1826 between the federal government and the Cippewa, Menominee, and Winnebago Indians, all vital elements in the fur trade in the upper Midwest. Part travel narrative, part ethnography, the 
                <title render="italic">Sketches</title> includes a detailed description of the trip across the Great Lakes undertaken by McKenney and Lewis Cass, later governor of Michigan Territory. The bulk of the volume, however, is devoted to a description of the "character," language, and beliefs of the Chippewa Indians and of the treaty negotiations held at the American Fur Company headquarters at Fond du Lac, Wisconsin. The artist James Otto Lewis accompanied the party, and his illustrations formed the basis for the 29 lithographic plates that appeared in the 
                <title render="italic">Sketches</title>.</p>
            <p>McKenney's efforts to establish a reference collection on the American Indian in the War Department (home of the Office of Indian Affairs) resulted in his collaboration with the artist Charles Bird King, among others, to accumulate portraits of prominent Native Americans. After leaving office, he collaborated with the writer, James Hall, conceiving a plan to publish these as a massive color plate book, adding biographies to accompany the portraits. Although he abandoned the project before completion, the McKenney and Hall 
                <title render="italic">History of the Indian Tribes of North America</title> remains an important work both in the history of printing and the history of American ethnography.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref4">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The manuscript of Thomas McKenney's 
                <title render="italic">Sketches of a Tour of the Lakes</title> is a fair copy of the original intended for use by an English publisher. The manuscript is bound in half leather over plain boards in three volumes with chaotic pagination.</p>
            <p>The manuscript contains a copy of the Chippewa (Ojibwa, Anishinabe) vocabulary using the Schoolcraft-Gallatin orthography, but it lacks the appendices that accompany the Lewis edition. Interspersed throughout the volumes are 29 watercolor illustrations that differ in detail from those in the Fielding Lewis edition of 1827, with somewhat stronger color. These include depictions of scenery along the Great Lakes, particularly the rock formations in Lake Superior, the American Fur Company headquarters, the council, a Chippewa dance, and portraits of Chippewa men and women.</p>
            <p>Native American Images Note : Twenty-nine watercolor illustrations by artist James Otto Lewis, companion images to Thomas Loraine McKenney’s three volume journal. Vividly colored, the sketches display landscapes, customs and portraits of the Chippewa in 1826. Of particular note, a portrait of O-Shee-Gwun, one of the signers of the Fond du Lac treaty at Lake Superior. See also the APS Photograph Collection for photographs of some sketches.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <prefercite id="ref6">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: Thomas McKenney, 
                <title render="italic">Sketches of a Tour of the Lakes</title>, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref7">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Gift of Thomas L. McKenney, 1831.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref8">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Recatalogued by rsc, 2002.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <bibliography id="ref9">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <bibref>Viola, Herman, 
                <title render="italic">Thomas L. McKenney : architect of America's early Indian policy, 1816-1830</title> (Chicago: Sage, 1974) 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: B M196v</bibref>
            <bibref>McKenney, Thomas Loraine, 
                <title render="italic">History of the Indian tribes of North America : With biographical sketches and anecdotes of the principal chiefs</title> [broadside] (Philadelphia: Bradford, 1830). 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 973 C683 no.399</bibref>
            <bibref>McKenney, Thomas Loraine, 
                <title render="italic">History of the Indian tribes of North America : With biographical sketches and anecdotes of the principal chiefs</title>, 3 vols. (Philadelphia : E. C. Biddle [etc.], 1836-1844)
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 970.1 M19</bibref>
            <bibref>McKenney, Thomas Loraine, 
                <title render="italic">A Catalogue of One Hundred and Seventeen Indian Portraits Representing Eighteen Different Tribes, Accompanied by a Few Brief Remarks on the Character &amp;c. of Most of Them</title> (Philadelphia: s.n., 1836). 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 970.6 M193c</bibref>
            <bibref>McKenney, Thomas Loraine, 
                <title render="italic">Sketches of a Tour to the Lakes, of the Character and Customs of the Chippeway Indians, and of Incidents Connected with the Treaty of Fond du Lac</title> (Baltimore: Fielding Lucas, 1827). 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 970.1 M191</bibref>
            <bibref>McKenney, Thomas Loraine, 
                <title render="italic">Memoirs, Official and Personal : with Sketches of Travels Among the Northern and Southern Indians; Embracing a War Excursion, and Descriptions of Scenes Along the Western Borders</title>, 2 vols. (N.Y.: New York : Paine and Burgess, 1846). 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 970.1 M19m</bibref>
        </bibliography>
        <otherfindaid id="ref10">
            <head>Other Finding Aids note</head>
            <p>Indexed in the online 
                <extref ns2:actuate="onLoad" ns2:show="new" ns2:href="http://www.amphilsoc.org/natam/search">Daythal Kendall Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society</extref>.</p>
        </otherfindaid>
        <odd id="ref42">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>This is a manuscript copy of Thomas McKenney’s Sketches of a Tour of the Lakes, which was a chronicle of his tour of the Great Lakes region when he served as Superintendent of Indian Affairs. His journal was eventually published in Baltimore in 1827. The original journal not only records his observations and interactions, but, as the federal official in charge of Indian policy, reflects his thinking on federal Indian policy. His observations also reflect, to some extent, his interpretation of Indian history. A color image of O Shau Gus Coday Way Gua (Mrs. Johnson) in included in the volume. This image graces the cover of the book in black and white. There are other watercolor sketches as well.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname source="ingest">Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Lewis, James Otto, 1799-1858</persname>
            <genreform source="leah">Art</genreform>
            <subject source="local">Eastern Woodlands Indians</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Government Affairs</subject>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Great Lakes--Description and travel</geogname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Indians of North America--Great Lakes (North America)</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Indians of North America--Treaties</subject>
            <genreform source="gmgpc">Landscapes</genreform>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Michigan--Description and travel</geogname>
            <subject source="leah">Native America</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Official Government Documents and Records</genreform>
            <subject source="lcsh">Ojibwa Indians</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Ojibwa language--Dictionaries--English</subject>
            <genreform source="gmgpc">Portraits</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Sketchbooks</genreform>
            <genreform source="leah">Travel Narratives and Journals</genreform>
            <genreform source="ingest">Watercolors</genreform>
            <geogname source="lcsh">Wisconsin--Description and travel</geogname>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref11" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>List of Illustrations</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref12" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>North River steam boat and safety barge, 
                            <emph render="italic">Lady Clinton</emph></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114999" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">1</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref13" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>O-Shau-Gus-Coday-Way-Gua, now Mrs. Johnson</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114998" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref14" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>White fish of the Lakes</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114997" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref15" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Indian dog train</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114996" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref16" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Indian snow shoe</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114995" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref17" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Indian canoe</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114994" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Front view American Fur Company's buildings, Fond du Lac</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114993" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Indian discovery dance</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114992" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                    <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Indian discovery dance" ns2:role="Image-Service" ns2:href="http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/fedora/repository/graphics:3300">
                        <daodesc>
                            <p>Indian discovery dance, 1826 </p>
                        </daodesc>
                    </dao>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Chippeway lodge of poles</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114991" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                    <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Chippeway lodge of poles" ns2:role="Image-Service" ns2:href="http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/fedora/repository/graphics:3301">
                        <daodesc>
                            <p>Chippeway lodge of poles, 1826 </p>
                        </daodesc>
                    </dao>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>O-Shee-Gwun (a squaw)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114990" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref22" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Chippeway widow</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114989" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                    <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Chippeway widow" ns2:role="Image-Service" ns2:href="http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/fedora/repository/graphics:3296">
                        <daodesc>
                            <p>Chippeway widow, 1826 </p>
                        </daodesc>
                    </dao>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref23" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Indian child's grave</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114988" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref24" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Indian council</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114987" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref25" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>O-Car-Gee-Wack (a squaw)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114986" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref26" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Female Chippeway of distinction</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114985" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Key-Way-No-Wut</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114984" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                    <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Key-Way-No-Wut" ns2:role="Image-Service" ns2:href="http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/fedora/repository/graphics:3297">
                        <daodesc>
                            <p>Key-Way-No-Wut, 1826 </p>
                        </daodesc>
                    </dao>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref28" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Chippeway Chief with his calumet and pouch</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114983" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref41" level="item">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Wa-Em-Boesh-Kaa</unittitle>
                            <unitdate>1826</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Wa-Em-Boesh-Kaa" ns2:role="Image-Service" ns2:href="http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/fedora/repository/graphics:3299">
                            <daodesc>
                                <p>Wa-Em-Boesh-Kaa, 1826 </p>
                            </daodesc>
                        </dao>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref29" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Back view American Fur Company's buildings, Fond du Lac</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114982" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Shin-Gua-Ba-Wossin</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114981" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref31" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Skeleton of a Chippeway lodge</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114980" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref32" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>The Vase -- Lake Superior</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114979" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref33" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Oblique view of the Doric Rock, Lake Superior</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114978" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref34" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Castle Rock, Lake Superior</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114977" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref35" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cave Rock -- Lake Superior</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114976" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref36" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>The Urn -- Lake Superior</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114975" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref37" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Chippeway nursing mother</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114974" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref38" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>View of Michilimackinac</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114973" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref39" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Indian solitary</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114972" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref40" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Indian woman carrying a child on a Journey</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114971" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
