<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.Ms.Coll.76.17</num>
                </titleproper>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T21:02-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="series">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Howard Houston, II Papers</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.Ms.Coll.76.17</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>8.0 Linear feet</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1903/1918" type="inclusive">1903-1918</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref274" label="Abstract">Henry Howard Houston II (1895-1918) was the son of a prominent Philadelphia family, the Houstons. He enjoyed a privileged upbringing, graduating from Chestnut Hill Academy in 1912 and from the University of Pennsylvania in 1916. Upon his graduation date, he enlisted in Battery C of the First Field Artillery, Pennsylvania National Guard, and was sent to the Texas and New Mexico borders in response to Pancho Villa's raids from Mexico. In January 1917, he volunteered with the American Field Ambulance Service in France during World War I, stationed near Verdun, where he was constantly under fire when performing his duty to pick up wounded soldiers from the trenches. Henry took a commission to serve with the French Army and enrolled in its transportation school. The French government awarded him the Croix de Guerre for gallantry under fire. When the U.S. entered the war, Henry resigned his commission in the French army and rejoined his Pennsylvania National Guard unit, the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade, 28th Division. He returned to the U.S., and received training as an aerial observer at Fort Sill, Oklahoma. It seems that, in early 1918, he returned a second time to France. In August 1918, German bombing squadrons attacked nightly, and Henry, then a lieutenant and personal aide to General Price, was killed south of Arcis-le-Ponsart while returning from an air field. He was 23. The bulk of this eight linear feet collection reflects Henry's personal life as a son, soldier, friend and lover, during the last three years of his life 1916 to 1918.</abstract>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <bioghist id="ref116">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>First Lieutenant Henry Howard Houston II, April 5, 1895-August 18, 1918. Born to Samuel Houston and Edith Atlee Corlies Houston in Chestnut Hill, Pennsylvania on April 5, 1895. His mother died days after his birth. Seven years later his father married Charlotte Harding Shephard Brown, who brought two children to the marriage. In 1910, Samuel and Charlotte welcomed the birth of their daughter, Eleanor.</p>
            <p>'Hennie' as he was known, attended Chestnut Hill Academy and the University of Pennsylvania, graduating in 1916. He was a sailor and accomplished soccer player. He enlisted in Battery C of the First Field Artillery, Pennsylvania National Guard, the same day he graduated and was sent to the Texas and New Mexico borders in response to Pancho Villa's raids from Mexico. In January 1917, he volunteered for the American Field Ambulance Service in France. Stationed near Verdun, he was frequently under fire while performing picking up wounded soldiers. He took a commission to serve with the French army, and by invitation, enrolled in the French Army Transportation School. He was awarded the Croix de Guerre for gallantry under fire.</p>
            <p>He resigned his commission when the United States entered the war and rejoined his Pennsylvania National Guard unit, the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade, 28th Division. He was trained as an aerial observer at Fort Sill, Oklahoma before returning to France. From France he wrote to his father in February 1918 about the School of Fire where he was receiving more training for aerial observation: "This is the branch of aviation for which all other branches exist. A fighting plane goes up merely to protect friendly observation planes and sink enemy craft. Artillery would be blind without aerial observation. By getting into this game I am not getting out of artillery but merely raising it to the 17th power. Don't worry, I won't get hurt."</p>
            <p>Brigade Commander General William Price requested that the well-trained Lieutenant Houston serve on his staff as a personal aide. On August 18, 1918, Houston was killed south of Arcis-le-Ponsart while returning from an airfield. He had volunteered to go to the airfield for the purpose of establishing more thorough cooperation between the aerial observers and the heavy batteries of the 108th Field Artillery, whose fire they were then directing.</p>
            <p>Henry Howard Houston, II is buried in the military cemetery in Suresnes, France. He was 23 years old when he was killed. In his honor, Henry's parents gave a stone building to the local American Legion and the building is named the Henry Howard Houston, 2nd Post.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref273">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The Henry Howard Houston, II Series (1895-1918, bulk 1910-1918) consists of material from throughout Houtson's life, including school report cards, early letters to his parents, and photographs from his childhood and college days. However, the majority of the the material is from his time in the ambulance service and the military, mainly correspondence, photographs and other material from his time in France during World War I.</p>
            <p>This series is rich in materials related to World War I history and early 20th century history of one of Philadelphia's most prominent families at that time, the Houstons. Those studying the regimental history of the 28th Division (Pennsylvania National Guard, "Iron Division") during World War I will find this collection valuable. Of special note is the correspondence between Henry and his parents, Samuel Frederic Houston and Charlotte Harding Houston. Also, of significance, a letter from Major General W.G. Price to Henry is included, dated February 15, 1918. In the Graphics Subseries are photographs of Henry and his division but also photographs from his time at Fort Bliss in Texas.</p>
            <p>The material is organized into eight subseries: Correspondence; Military Communication; Personal; Bound Volumes; Printed Materials; Graphics; Maps; and Realia. Most of the series are arranged alphabetically, except where the Arrangement Note indicates otherwise.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref298">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>Material about the life of Henry Houston, II, including condolence letters to his parents and information about the cemetery in which he is buried can be found in the Samuel Frederic Houston Papers, Series 18 of the Smith-Houston-Morris-Ogden Family Papers, Ms Coll 76.</p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <bibliography id="ref290">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <p>A list of references pertaining to Henry Howard Houston II and the Houston family.</p>
            <bibref>Contosta, David R. 
                <emph render="italic">A Philadelphia Family: The Houstons and Woodwards of Chestnut Hill</emph>. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1988. Print.</bibref>
            <bibref>Houston, E. Rankin. 
                <emph render="italic">History of the Houston Families and their Descendants 1450-1912 with a Genealogical Record</emph>. Carlisle: Carlisle Printing Company, 1912. Print.</bibref>
            <bibref>Houston, Samuel Rutherford. 
                <emph render="italic">Brief Biographical Accounts of Many Members of the Houston Family Accompanied by a Genealogical Table</emph>. Cincinnati: Elm Street Printing Company, 1882. Print.</bibref>
            <bibref>Martin, Edward. 
                <emph render="italic">The Twenty-Eighth Division Pennsylvania's Guard in the World War, Volume IV</emph>. Pittsburgh: 28th Division Publishing Co., 1924. Print.</bibref>
            <bibref>Roberts Jr., Frank C. 
                <emph render="italic">The Houstons of Philadelphia</emph>. New York: The Newcomer Society in North America, 1954. Print.</bibref>
        </bibliography>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname source="local">Houston, Charlotte</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="local">Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952</persname>
            <corpname source="ingest">University of Pennsylvania</corpname>
            <subject source="ingest">Philadelphia. Citizens</subject>
            <subject source="LCNAF">United States. Army--History--Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1916</subject>
            <subject source="ingest">United States. Army--History--World War, 1914-1918</subject>
            <subject source="ingest">World War, 1914-1918 --Regimental histories --United States --28th (Iron) division</subject>
            <subject source="ingest">World War, 1914-1918--France</subject>
            <subject source="ingest">World War, 1914-1918--Regimental histories--United States</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref2" level="subseries">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Subseries A. Correspondence</unittitle>
                    <unitdate normal="1901/1918" type="inclusive">1901, 1906, 1916-1918</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref218">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>The Correspondence sub-series consists mainly of Henry’s correspondence with his parents, Samuel F. Houston and Charlotte Harding Houston, while Henry served in the armed forces. The second largest category of letters comes from letters to and from his friends. There are a few touching letters between Henry and his youngest half-sister, Eleanor Houston.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref219">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>These letters are generally arranged alphabetically by the last name of the sender. Under that sender's last name, the letters are arranged chronologically. Where the last name of the sender is unclear, the letter is arranged alphabetically by the sender's first name.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref202" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 August 23</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Allen, W.</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref117" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 January 6</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="local" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Andrews, D</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref118">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Letter from D. Andrews, Henry's friend, to Henry. Fraternity activities.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref119" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 October 17</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Bandellini, F</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref120" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Bébé. Letter to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 August 1</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref121">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Brief letter of amorous nature. Year uncertain, but most likely 1918.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref122" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 May 7</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Coan, Ray</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref123">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Last name uncertain, could be "Coan" or "Coun."</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref124" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cousin. Letter to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref125">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Letter written in a child's handwriting. Initialed "HHW" at the end.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref126" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1916 October 15</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Charlotte</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref127" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 April-August</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Charlotte</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref128" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 February 28, 1918 August 4</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="local" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Smith, Houston, Eleanor</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref129" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Mrs. Graham</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 March 19</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref130" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1910 October 18</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref131" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1915 June-July</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref132" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1916 July-August</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref133" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>4.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1916 October-November</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref134" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>11.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 January-April</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref135" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>10.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 May-October, November</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref136">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>The year of the November letter is unknown, but most likely 1917.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref137" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>9.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 January-June</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref145" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref138" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref208" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Charlotte Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref146" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Eleanor Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1910 August 5, 1917 January 16</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref149" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Mrs. Henry Howard Houston, Grandmother</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1903 July 19</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref150" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Eugénie Iselin</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 July,1918 July</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref147" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Harry Iselin</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 April 30</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref148">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Letter to Cousin.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref151" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Harry Iselin</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 June 8</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref205" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Samuel F. Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1915, July 11</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref153" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Samuel F. Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>9.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1916 June-October</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref155" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Samuel F. Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>6.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 January-March</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref154" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Samuel F. Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 April-September</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref156" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Samuel F. Houston</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>8.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 February-July</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref157" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Santa Claus</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1901 November 25</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref158" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to unknown</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1916</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref159">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Composed in Albuquerque, New Mexico.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref160" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Telegram to unknown</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 August 13</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="dacs" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref161">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Telegram sent from Paris, France.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref162" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>7.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 January-February</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref163" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 March-April</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref164" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>4.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 May-June</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref165" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 June-July</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref166" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 July-August</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref167" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>unknown</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref168">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Letter fragment.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref169" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 July 13</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="local" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Iselin, Helene</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref170" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Nance. Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 May 23</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref192" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Peg. Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 June 30</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref193" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1913 June 9</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Pilger, Richard</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <odd id="ref194">
                        <head>General note</head>
                        <p>Receipt for speeding ticket</p>
                    </odd>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref191" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 February 15</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Price, Jr., W.G., Major General</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref203" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to unknown</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>unknown</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Rex, Hilary</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref299">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Henry was most likely the recipient of this Christmas card, because this card came from the U.S. Flying Corps and Henry was part of aerial observation.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref195" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 November 11</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Thompson, Hank B.</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref300" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918 July 29</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="local" role="Author (aut)">Trotter, Betty</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref206" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1916 February 15</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <corpname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">University of Pennsylvania</corpname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref204" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917 May 11</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="local" source="local" role="Author (aut)">Whitaker, Samuel</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref4" level="subseries">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Subseries B. Military Communications</unittitle>
                    <unitdate normal="1916/1918" type="inclusive">1916-1918</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref220">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>The Military Communications sub-series mainly consists of official letters and telegrams to Henry from the War Department of the United States and the French military. They detail orders which transfer Henry to a different division or location, or promote Henry to a new position.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref221">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>These documents are arranged alphabetically by the first letter of an organization's name. For example, "W" for "War Department," and "F" for "French Military."</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref46" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>7th Division</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 September</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref47" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>28th Division</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>11.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1918" type="inclusive">1917 August- 1917 October, 1918 February-1918 April 10</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref295">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Correspondence from the Pennsylvania National Guard Division, 28th from multiple creators. Includes fitness report signed off by General W. G. Price.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <controlaccess>
                        <corpname rules="aacr" source="local">Pennsylvania. National Guard. Infantry Division, 28th.. -- Correspondence</corpname>
                    </controlaccess>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref48" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>53rd Artillery Brigade</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1918/1918">1918 April 26-1918 July 10</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref49" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>American Ambulance Hospital in Paris</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref50" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Commonwealth of PA, Adjutant- General's Office</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 July 3</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref52" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Military Correspondence, 1914</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1914/1914">1914</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref53" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 1 of 5</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>4.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref62" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 2 of 5</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>7.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref63" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 3 of 5</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 February 16-1917 July 25</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref64" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 4 of 5</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>4.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Davis, David J.</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref65" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 5 of 5</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>5.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref54" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Military Correspondence, undated Folder 1 of 2</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>4.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref66" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Military Correspondence, undated Folder 2 of 2</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref58" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II Travel Documents to France</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>8.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917, undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <odd id="ref59">
                        <head>General note</head>
                        <p>Tickets and Pass</p>
                    </odd>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref55" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>National Guard, Pennsylvania</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 June 29</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref56" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>National Security League Certificate</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1916/1916">1916 April 10</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref57" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Ordnance Department, USA</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 December 18</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref60" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>United States War Department Correspondence</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>7.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1916/1918" type="inclusive">1916 October 28, 1918 January 24, 1918 March 26, undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref5" level="subseries">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Subseries C. Personal</unittitle>
                    <unitdate>1906-1912, 1916-1917</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref222">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>The Personal sub-series consists of some of Henry’s personal effects. These include his handwritten draft of a poem in iambic pentameter while he was in grade school, and its published form in the school newsletter. There are also his handwritten notes while he took lessons in artillery mechanics during his time in the service. In the back of this sub-series, there are folders labeled “Ephemera.” These include invitations and programs to events in honor of the 28th Division, which Henry may likely have attended.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref223">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the first letter of an organization's name. For example, "C" for "Chestnut Hill Academy," "U" for "University of Pennsylvania."</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref41" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Battery "C", PA, Reception Program</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1916/1916">1916</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref38" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Chestnut Hill Academy. The Wissahickon (Publication)</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1912/1912">1912</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref32" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II. Chestnut Hill Academy Report Cards</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 box</extent>
                            <extent>12 Folders</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1906/1912" type="inclusive">1906-1912</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref43" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II. Immunization Certification</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1916/1916">1916 June 23</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref45" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II. Invitation for a Ball</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref37" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II. Poem "The Race" Hand Written</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref44" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II. Receipt for Tailored Clothes</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 January 31</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref35" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II. School Papers</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>4.0 folders</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <odd id="ref36">
                        <head>General note</head>
                        <p>School Papers of Dr. Robert Bridges, the Poetry of Hanefield, Lawrence Hope, Rudyard Kipling, Henry Newbert, Alfred Noyes, Robert Service, and Francis Thompson</p>
                    </odd>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref33" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II. United States Map</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref34">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Colored with crayons</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref42" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Menu in French of French Cuisine</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="fre"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">[October] 1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref40" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>University of Pennsylvania. Soccer Team, 1915 (News Clipping)</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1915/1915">1915 March</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref39" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>University of Pennsylvania Tickets and Brochures</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>12.0 items</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1911/1917" type="inclusive">1911-1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref6" level="subseries">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Subseries D. Bound Volumes</unittitle>
                    <unitdate normal="1917/1918" type="inclusive">1917-1918, and undated</unitdate>
                </did>
                <arrangement id="ref281">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>The items in this sub-series are arranged alphabetically.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <scopecontent id="ref280">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This sub-series of bound volumes contains a number of personal notebooks and journals. The bulk of the materials are notes and journals from his time in artillery school. There is also a type-written transcript of some of Henry's journal entries as well as an unused booklet of postcards from France.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 id="ref229" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Abbaye, N.- D. d'Igny Postcards</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 folder</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref301" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard Journal</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1914/1915" type="bulk">Bulk, 1914-1915</unitdate>
                        <unitdate normal="1914/1916" type="inclusive">1914-1916</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref302">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This black leatherbound journal contains Henry's concise journal entries. The majority of the entries are between 1914-1915; only a few a recorded in 1916.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref303" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard Journal</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref304">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This small red leatherbound journal contains lengthy entries by Henry during the time that he was stationed in France.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref305" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard Poems</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1914</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref306">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This large red leatherbound journal contains a few of Henry's poems written in his own hand. A poem on a looseleaf sheet of paper is folded within the journal. Three photographs of Henry's grave is also enclosed in the journal.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref307" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard List of Card Recipients and Addresses</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref308">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>In a small notebook, a list of card recipients and their addresses is recorded in Henry's own hand.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref309" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard Artillery Class Notes</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>unknown</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref310">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This notebook contains copious notes on artillery machinery in Henry's own hand.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref233" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard Artillery and Mechanical Class Notes in France</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref234" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard Field Gunnery Class Notes Fort Sill, Oklahoma</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref230" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard Pocket Journal, Poetry Composition, and School Grades</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 folder</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref232" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard Transcript of Journal</unittitle>
                        <langmaterial>
                            <language langcode="eng"/>
                        </langmaterial>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 March</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref311" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Zeta Psi's Memorial Certificate in Honor of Henry Howard Houston, II</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref312">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This memorial certificate, issued by Zeta Psi, honors members of the Zeta Psi fraternity who gave their lives during World War I.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref7" level="subseries">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Subseries E. Printed Materials</unittitle>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate normal="1911/1962" type="inclusive">1911-1962</unitdate>
                </did>
                <arrangement id="ref283">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>This sub-series is arranged into boxes determined by subject matter. For example: those materials pertaining to France or the western front of World War I are included in the box labeled "France" and materials pertaining to Henry Howard Houston II as a student at the University of Pennsylvania are included in the box labeled "University of Pennslyvania. The contents of each box are organized alphabetically.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <scopecontent id="ref284">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>This sub-series is a collection of printed materials covering a wide range of topics including information about the World War I and the Western Front, field artillery, the University of Pennsylvania, and newspaper clippings.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 id="ref16" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subsubseries 1 - France</unittitle>
                        <unitdate normal="1915/1920" type="inclusive">1915, 1917, 1919, 1920</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref285">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This subsub-series of Printed Materials consists of published works relating to France and the western front of World War I.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c03 id="ref19" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Armistice Glade and Monument</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate>unknown</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref21">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>A small booklet about the monument for the armistice built in France.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref20" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>La Bataille de Verdun: un Guide, un Panorama, une Histoire</unittitle>
                            <langmaterial>
                                <language langcode="fre"/>
                            </langmaterial>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1919/1919">1919</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref92">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Clermont-Ferrand, Michelin &amp; co, c1919. Print.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref27">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Book detailing the Battle of Verdun. Book is in French. Contains dried and pressed flowers from Verdun.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <controlaccess>
                            <subject source="LCNAF">Battlefields--France--Verdun</subject>
                        </controlaccess>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref23" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>La Belgique et l'Allemagne</unittitle>
                            <langmaterial>
                                <language langcode="fre"/>
                            </langmaterial>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1915/1915">1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref29">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Informational book about Belgians and Germans, in French. Contains a handkerchief.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref93">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Londres: Imprime par Harrison et Fils, 1915. Print.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <controlaccess>
                            <geogname source="LCNAF">Belgium</geogname>
                            <subject source="local">World War I -- Germany</subject>
                        </controlaccess>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref24" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Carnival for Wounded</unittitle>
                            <langmaterial>
                                <language langcode="fre"/>
                            </langmaterial>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 July 14</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref30">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Pamphlet detailing the events of a carnival/festival put on for the wounded. Pamphlet is in French.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref25" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Extracts from the History of the American field service in France, "Friends of France," 1914-1917</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1920/1920">1920</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <corpname source="naf" role="Author (aut)">American Field Service.</corpname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref31">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Small booklet of extracts from the History of the American Field Service in France.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref94">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Boston and New York, Houghton Mifflin company, 1920.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref231" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Nelson Doubleday Complete War Map of Western Europe</unittitle>
                            <langmaterial>
                                <language langcode="eng"/>
                            </langmaterial>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1918/1918">1918</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref282">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>This is a printed, foldable pocket map of western Europe during World War I.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref211" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Rand Mcnally War Map of the French Front</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate>unknown</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref212">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>This is a published, folded pocket map of the French front during World War I. It shows the battle lines of 1914 and 1918.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref22" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Rheims and the battle for its possession</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1919/1919">1919</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref28">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Published book detailing the battle of Rheims. Contains dried and pressed flowers from Rheims.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref95">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Clermont-Ferrand, Michelin &amp; co, c1920. Print.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <controlaccess>
                            <subject source="LCNAF">Battlefields--France--Rheims</subject>
                        </controlaccess>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref17" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subsubseries 2 - Miscellaneous</unittitle>
                        <unitdate normal="1911/1918" type="inclusive">1911, 1914-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref286">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This subsub-series of Printed Materials consists of miscellaneous printed works either owned by or pertaining to Henry Howard Houston II. There are several religious texts (hymnals, prayer books, etc) along with a book he received as a gift, a newspaper, and two editions of a local Philadelphia newsletter.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c03 id="ref67" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>The Prize of Life</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1914/1914">1914</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <persname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason</persname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref68">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Small book that was given to Henry Howard Houston II by his Aunt Martha.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref96">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Boston, New York [etc.] The Pilgrim press [c1914] Print.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref69" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>In Honour: An Elegy by a Father</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1915/1915">1915</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref70">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Small booklet dedicated to a soldier who died at the battle of Ypres in 1915. Markings in the margins.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref97">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>London: Constable and Company LTD., 1915. Print.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref71" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Newsletter - The Wissahickon</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1912/1918" type="inclusive">1912-1918</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref72">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Two editions of "The Wissahickon" newsletter from April 1912 and November 1918.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref73" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Prayer Book and Hymnal</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1911/1911">1911 March 12</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref74">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Small pocket sized prayer book and hymnal given to Henry Howard Houston II for his confirmation on March 12, 1911.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref75" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Prayer Book for Soldiers and Sailors</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref76">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Prayer book given to Henry Howard Houston II by his sister Eleanor.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref98">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Philadelphia: Bishop White Prayer Book Society, 1917.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref77" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Prayer Book - Intercessions for the Church: War Edition</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1914/1918" type="inclusive">1914-1918</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref78">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Prayer book. Containts a small picture and prayer insert.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref79" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Prayer book</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate>1917</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref80">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>very small prayer pamphlet.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref209" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>New York Times</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1916/1916">1916 January 11</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref215">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>This is a folded edition of the New York Times newspaper dated January 11, 1916.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <phystech id="ref293">
                            <head>Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note</head>
                            <p>This document is folded and fragile. It is flagged in the box and should be looked at by the Conservation Department.</p>
                        </phystech>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref15" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subsubseries 3 - US Military</unittitle>
                        <unitdate normal="1911/1939" type="inclusive">1911, 1916, 1917, 1939, undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref287">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This subsub-series of Printed Materials contains documents and texts pertaining to the United States military, specifically Henry Howard Houston II's unit, the 28th division of the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c03 id="ref83" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>General Orders No. 32</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1916/1916">1916 July 28</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <corpname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">United States. War Dept.</corpname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref84">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Pamphlet containing the War Department's general orders no. 32.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref85" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Instruction Pamphlet for Gunner's Examination in the Field Artillery, Service Schools Bulletin No. 6</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref87">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Brooklyn: Second FIeld Artillery, N.G.N.Y.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref89" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Official History of the Militia and the National Guard of the State of Pennsylvania</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1939/1939">1939</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref90">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>20th Anniversary Edition booklet special issue dedicated to Major General WM. G. Price, Jr and the 28th Division. Bookmark on page commemorating Henry Howard Houston II.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref91">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Compiled and Published by Colonel Charles J. Hendler. Philadelphia, PA. December 1939.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref13" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Price, William Gray. Activities and Citations of the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade 28th Division United States Army: World War, 1914-1918</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1919/1919">1919</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref14">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Pamphlet describing the activities and citations of the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref86">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Chester, PA: Press of Chester Times, 1919. Print.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref99" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>The Service and its Insignia</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref100">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Philadelphia: Bailey, Banks &amp; Biddle Company. 1917.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref101">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>A small pamphlet detailing the various signs, symbols, and insignia of the United States Armed Forces.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref81" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Drill regulations for Field Artillery</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1911/1911">1911</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <corpname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">United States. War Dept.</corpname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref82">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Henry Howard Houston II's copy of drill regulations for horse and light field artillery in the United States Army.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref88">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Washington, Govt. Print. Off., 1911.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subsubseries 4 - University of Pennsylvania</unittitle>
                        <unitdate normal="1916/1918" type="inclusive">1916-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref288">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This subsub-series of Printed Materials contains published works relating to the University of Pennsylvania and the Zeta Psi fraternity, of which Henry Howard Houston II was a member.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c03 id="ref105" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>160th Commencement pamphlet</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1916/1916">1916 June 21</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <corpname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">University of Pennsylvania</corpname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref106">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Brochure for the 160th commencement ceremony.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref107" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Alumni Register</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1917/1918" type="inclusive">June 1917 &amp; November 1918</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <corpname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">University of Pennsylvania. General Alumni Society</corpname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref108">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Two editions of the monthly alumni register published by the General Alumni Society.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref102" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>The Pennsylvania Gazette</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1924/1924">1924 December 19</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <corpname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">University of Pennsylvania</corpname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref103">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>This edition of the PA Gazette has an article on page 252 about the Houston Cup given to the UPenn soccer team in memory of Henry Howard Houston II who was a member of the team while a student at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <scopecontent id="ref104">
                            <head>Publishing Info</head>
                            <p>Published by the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref111" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Fraternity House Photographs</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate>unknown</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref112">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Interior and exterior photographs of the Zeta Psi fraternity house at the intersection of 33rd and Walnut streets in Philadelphia, PA.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                        <controlaccess>
                            <corpname source="naf" role="Other (oth)">Zeta Psi Fraternity. Sigma Chapter.</corpname>
                        </controlaccess>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref109" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Sigma Zetes doing their bit</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1917/1917">1917 November 1</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <corpname source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Zeta Psi Fraternity. Sigma Chapter.</corpname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref110">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Broadside from Sigma chapter of Zeta Psi fraternity at University of Pennsylvania with list of fraternity alumni in service during the war. Henry Howard Houston II is listed approximately 1/3 of the way down the right hand column.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref113" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>The Circle of Zeta Psi</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1918/1918">1918 November</unitdate>
                            <origination label="creator">
                                <corpname source="naf" role="Author (aut)">Zeta Psi Fraternity. Sigma Chapter.</corpname>
                            </origination>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref114">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>National newsletter for Zeta Psi fraternity. Article of Henry Howard Houston II and his death on pages 57-58.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref182" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subsubseries 5 - Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1936, 1962</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref289">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This subsub-series of Printed Materials is comprised of newspaper clippings, many of which are related to Henry Howard Houston II's death, the anniversary of his death, or the role of artillery during World War I. Because these materials are oversize, they are located in an oversize box separate from the other Printed Materials.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c03 id="ref183" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>From Sam Houston to Henry Howard Houston II</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate>July 1918 and unknown</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref184">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>One pouch contains newspaper clippings that were loosely mixed in with some correspondence between Sam and Henry Houston. All of them pertain to the war.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref185" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Sky Spies</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1962/1962">September 28, 1962</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref186">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>A brief newspaper article about artillery spotters in balloons during World War I.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref187" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Newspapers</unittitle>
                            <physdesc>
                                <extent>1.0 item</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                            <unitdate normal="1918/1936" type="inclusive">1918-1936</unitdate>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref188">
                            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                            <p>Three large folders of newspapers, newsletters,and pamphlets spanning the years 1918 to 1936.Includes a large full page article about Henry Howard Houston II from the Germantown Independent Gazette Aug 18, 1921.</p>
                        </scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref8" level="subseries">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Subseries F. Graphics</unittitle>
                    <unitdate normal="1914/1921" type="inclusive">1914-1918, unknown</unitdate>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref224">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>The Graphics sub-series consistes of large, mid-size, and small photographs. Most of these photographs capture Henry’s surroundings during the time he served in the armed forces. Therefore, a large portion depict France during World War I, and some may depict his surroundings during his training period (Fort Sill, Oklahoma; the Texas-Mexico border). They show the everyday life of a World War I soldier and, from the stark images of bombed out buildings, the ravages of war itself.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref225">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>For each photo or group of photos, we made an educated estimate of the most prominent location or person depicted in the photo. We then arranged the photos alphabetically based on the first letter of that prominent noun. For example, "B" for "Bombed Building," "H" for "Henry Howard Houston, II," and "F" for "France." Where the location was unknown and there was no date, those photos were categorized under "U" for "Undated."</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref235" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Arc de Triomphe, Print</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1919</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref236" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Aerial Photograph, French Regions</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref237" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Bombed Building, before and after</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref260" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cathedrale de Reims, Print</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref243" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cathedrale de St.-Jean - La Somme, France - Print</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref244" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Enumerated Description of Photographs</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref245">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>It is unclear to which photographs this list corresponds. However, the photos would be from Henry's time in the armed service.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref238" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>France, small photographs</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1916, undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref240" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>France, small photographs</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1918, undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref239" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>France, mid and small-sized photographs</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1918, undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref241" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Battlescene Postcards, unsent</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1914-1921, undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref242" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>French Battlefield Photos</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref246" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder I</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref247" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 2</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref248" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 3</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref249" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 4</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref250" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 5</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref252" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 6</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref253" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II - Boat to France</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref251" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II and Brother, Childhood</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref216" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II, Childhood Album</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>unknown</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref217">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This large leather album chronicles Henry's childhood and teenage years with many photographs. It is oversize.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <arrangement id="ref272">
                        <head>Arrangement note</head>
                        <p>Original order was preserved in this album.</p>
                    </arrangement>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref254" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II - Mexico</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref270" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II - Military Portraits, Oversize</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref271">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>This oversize blue box contains a negative print press from which Henry's image was imprinted, two military portraits of Henry, a small leather album of Henry while he was in the service, and oversize photos of Henry in the army and at Penn.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref255" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II - Portrait Photographs</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref256" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II - Postcards - Friends</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref257" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Houston, Henry Howard II - S.S.U. #12 - Group Photo</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1917 January</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref258" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Maison de Jeanne d'Arc - Domzeny - France, Print</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref259" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Marais sur le front americain, Print</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref261" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>"Pour Madame Houston" Postcards</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref262" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Small Photos and Accompanying Enumerated Descriptive List</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref263">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>The list in Henry's handwriting has numbers paired with descriptions that correspond to the numbers on the back of each photo.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref264" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Unknown Persons and Buildings</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref265">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>On the back of each photo are numbers that may correspond to the numbers and descriptions in the "Enumerated Description of Photographs" list.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref266" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Unknown Persons and Building</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref267">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>On the back of each photo are numbers that may correspond to the numbers and descriptions in the "Enumerated Description of Photographs" list.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref268" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Unknown Persons and Building</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref269">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>On the back of each photo are numbers that may correspond to the numbers and descriptions in the "Enumerated Description of Photographs" list.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref9" level="subseries">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Subseries G. Maps</unittitle>
                    <unitdate normal="1914/1918" type="inclusive">1914-1918</unitdate>
                </did>
                <arrangement id="ref214">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>The Maps are not arranged in alphabetical order, but in accordance with the size of each map with a view to protect and preserve the material. A Rand McNally map of the western front battle lines of 1914 and 1918 is located in Subseries D - Bound Volumes, due to its smaller physical size.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <scopecontent id="ref226">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>These Maps are located in the Oversize section of the collection. The Maps sub-series consists of very large maps of western Europe, France, and specific French regions. A couple maps have Henry’s name written on the back in pencil.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 id="ref189" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Maps of France - Oversized folder</unittitle>
                        <unitdate normal="1914/1918" type="inclusive">1914-1918</unitdate>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref190">
                        <head>Maps</head>
                        <p>One oversized folder contains: -One small map of the area surrounding Ypres that shows the approximate lines of advance for the Battle of Ypres. Dated November 6, 1917 - April 29, 1918. -One large map of Reims and the surrounding area in great detail. -One large map of Meaux(?), France. "Meaux" is written in pencil on the back. -One large map of Soissons. "H H Houston" written in pencil on the back. -One large map of the Region Laon-Soissons. "H H Houston" written in pencil on the back.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <controlaccess>
                        <subject source="local">Maps</subject>
                        <subject source="local">World War I -- France</subject>
                        <subject source="lcsh">World War, 1914-1918</subject>
                    </controlaccess>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref10" level="subseries">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Subseries H. Realia</unittitle>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref227">
                    <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                    <p>The Realia sub-series consists of large to small cultural artifacts. Of significance are (a) ambulance armbands in white with a red cross which Henry, as an ambulance driver, may have worn; and (b) a “US Army” sewn lapel which Henry may have worn.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <arrangement id="ref228">
                    <head>Arrangement note</head>
                    <p>The Realia were arranged with three goals in mind: (a) to keep artifacts which accompanied each other together; (b) to keep objects of like size together; and (c) to protect fragile items.</p>
                </arrangement>
                <c02 id="ref171" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Realia Box 1 - Keys, Lock, Bullet, Metal Pellet</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref172">
                        <head>Box Contents</head>
                        <p>-Three small metal keys -One large iron key -One small lock -One large bullet -One small metal pellet/ball</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref173" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Realia Box 2 - Linen handkerchief and oil painting on wood</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref174">
                        <head>Box Contents</head>
                        <p>-One small white linen handkerchief with blue letter "P" and red letters "A" and "F" embroidered on it. -An oil painting of a cemetery on a piece of wood.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref175" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Realia Box 3 - Flag and Handkerchief</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref176">
                        <head>Box Contents</head>
                        <p>-One large white linen handkerchief with "Henry Houston" embroidered on it. date 1899. -One large red linen flag with a white five point star sewn into the center.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref177" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Realia Box 4 - Decorative Asian Handkerchief, Pocket Square Purse, Bowtie, Ambulance Armband, Armband with Numbers and Red Cord.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref178">
                        <head>Box Contents</head>
                        <p>-One purse made of a fragile purple cloth with flags (USA, Romania, France, Japan, Belgium). -One decorative handkerchief with asian theme. -Armband with numbers "87" and a red cord. -Ambulance armband (red cross on white background) -Various striped, colored ribbons</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref316" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Realia Box 5 - War Related Realia</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref317">
                        <head>Box Contents</head>
                        <p>- One large black leather wallet, with the yellow inscription "H. H. Houston, Philadelphia" inscribed - One thermometer encased in a blue box - Two shells welded together as a curiousity - A box which had contained Philadelphia soil. An inscription states that this soil had been placed on Henry's grave in Suresnes, France. - One small beaded ring which depicts the ambulance cross (white, with a red cross in the center).</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref179" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Realia Box 6 - Miscellaneous realia</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref181">
                        <head>Box Contents</head>
                        <p>-Two felt bicentennial armbands with years 1740 and 1940 -Ticket stub for transportation between El Paso and Tobin, Texas -Unknown containter lid with condolences for Henry Howard Houston II's death -Henry Howard Houston II's money: 4x $1 silver bank notes from 1899 and 1x 1904 gold $5 coin. -A toy airplane made from a bullet -Dried Flowers removed from bottom of larger storage box that came with accession of manuscript collection. -One Unites States Army Badge -One cloth ambulance armband -One fabric cord -One pencil sharpened by Henry Howard Houston II</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
