<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.974.8.L52-ead.xml">PUBLIC "-//American Philosophical Society LIBRARY//TEXT(US::PAAV::974.8 L52:: Peter Legaux Journal of the Vine Company of Pennsylvania)//EN" "legaux.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>Peter Legaux
                    <lb/>Journal of the Vine Company of Pennsylvania
                    <date type="span">1803-1827</date>
                    <num>Mss.974.8.L52</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by rsc</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>1/2003</date>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T18:27-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>ENG</langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Journal of the Vine Company of Pennsylvania</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.974.8.L52</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid13300001" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">1-4</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>4.0 Volume(s)</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1803/1827" type="inclusive">1803-1827</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">Initially proposed by Peter Legaux at a meeting of the American Philosophical Society in 1793, the Vine Company of Pennsylvania was a stock company that encouraged the domestic production of grapes, wines, and brandy, and dissemination of knowledge about viticulture. After its incorporation in 1802, the Company operated vineyards on Legaux's farm at Spring Mill, 13 miles northwest of Philadelphia, until it failed in 1822. The three volumes of Journals of the Vine Company of Pennsylvania record the daily operations of America's first commercial vineyard bewteeen 1803 and 1814. Kept by the superintendent, Peter Legaux, the journals provide careful records of weather, planting, harvesting and other field work, as well as some of the doings of the officers and shareholders of the Company. The fourth volume is essentially a weather diary kept by Legaux at Spring Mill from 1822 until his death in 1827. The last volume of Vine Company records covering the last eight years of its operation, 1814-1822, has been lost.</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref1" label="General Physical Description note">4 vols.</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref26" label="Paging">LH-MV-E-13</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Legaux, Peter,1748-1827.</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>In January 1793, Peter Legaux submitted a plan the American Philosophical Society for "the establishment of the Vine culture in Pennsylvania by means of public subscription, authorized and protected by Government." In 1785, Legaux, a Francophone emigrant from Saint Domingue, purchased Mount Joy, the former estate of Anthony Morris overlooking the Schuylkill River at Spring Mill, 13 miles northwest of Philadelphia, and began farming.</p>
            <p>From early in his residence at Spring Mill, Legaux appears to have conceived his farm as a place to promote advanced agricultural practices, including viticulture, and he indulged a variety of scientific interests that earned him election to the American Philosophical Society in July 1789. Legaux read works on electricity, assisted Jean Pierre Blanchard on the first manned balloon flight in America in 1793, and he donated a book on the history of Surinam, yet to his peers he was been best known for his careful meteorological observations at Spring Mill. From as early as 1787, Legaux built upon the work of Rittenhouse and Rush. The traveler François Alexandre Rochefoucauld-Liancourt found Legaux to be "dissatisfied with everyone" and regarded him as a "worthless and litigious man," but Legaux was acquainted with a wide and important circle, including Thomas Jefferson, Peter Stephen Du Ponceau, Stephen Girard, and John Vaughan, and carried some weight within the robust French community in Philadelphia.</p>
            <p>Following Legaux's proposal to the APS, the Pennsylvania legislature passed an act authorizing the incorporation of a company for promoting culture of the vine. A subscription was raised and shares issued to some of Philadelphia's most important merchants and friends of improvement, from Robert Morris and Benjamin Rush to Bohl Bohlen, Israel Whelen, John Wachsmuth, and Benjamin Franklin Bache, as well as the French minister, Citizen Gênet. Sales, however, did not meet expectations, and the project languished until April 1800, when the Pennsylvania Commissioners for the Cultivation of the Vine liberalized the original act to stimulate stock sales. After a public notice was placed in the 
                <title render="italic">Pennsylvania Gazette</title> in April 1800, encouraging the formation of a company to encourage viticulture in the state and to train vine dressers, 1,000 shares were made available at $20 each.</p>
            <p>Having issued over 550 shares, Governor Thomas McKean, a subscriber himself, directed that the Vine Company be incorporated in January 1802, and in June of the following year, Legaux was hired as superintendant of the vineyards at a rate of $300 per year. He oversaw the daily operations, the planting, grafting, weeding, and harvesting, and communicated regularly with the officers of society, including Peter Stephen Du Ponceau, Benjamin Say, Mathew Carey, Stephen Girard, Bernard McMahon, and Thomas Hodgson.</p>
            <p>Legaux experimented with different varieties of grape and different techniques of raising them, but the Company was never as profitable as hoped. It failed to make its debts and its vineyards were seized and sold at public auction in 1822. Legaux thereafter remained at Spring Mill, farming and recording the weather, but was less in the public eye. Shortly after recapitulating the events of 1826 with a note on the deaths of his "dear friends and the friends of the human kind," John Adams and Thomas Jefferson, Legaux fell ill with fever. In January 1827, he scrawled a journal entry "I am very sick... Like Death... and in Great Suffrances from head to feet &amp;c &amp;c and can do Nothing Except to horribly Complain against Nature &amp; God!!!!!!" His last entry was made at the end of March. He was survived by his wife Catherine Bosler and their three daughters.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref4">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The Journals of the Vine Company of Pennsylvania consist of four volumes documenting the daily work performed under the auspices of Peter Legaux at the Company's vineyards at Spring Mills, Pennsylvania, America's first commercial winery. Terse, written in Legaux's Frenchified English (and rarely in French), Legaux was a meticulous recorder of the work on the vines performed by his hired hands and vine cutters, and kept careful meteorlogical records. He also recorded communications from the officers of the Vine Company.</p>
            <p>Legaux's notoriously abrupt personality occasionally makes itself known, complaining frequently about the poor condition of his vineyards, the need for better weeding and tending the vines and, on occasion, about the officers of the Company.</p>
            <p>The journals contain a good deal of detailed information about pests and weather conditions as they affected crops, and some information regarding Legaux's experimentation with different varieties of grape and methods of plating and tending them. Other details are even more revealing:</p>
            <p>
                <blockquote>
                    <p>in the following years, it is asbolutly necessary where the Grapes Begain to come ripe to hired two mens for the Nights, one to warren in the one Night and the other one other night with one Good Dog, until the fruit is converted in vine or Brandy or disposed of by the officiers of the Vine Compy. It will do very well also to put several trapes in to the vineyards &amp;c this fruit is soo tempting that it is impossible to garde him from the rapacity of the people, notwithstanding that I did give present of mine to every of my Neigbourgs (September 25, 1810).</p>
                </blockquote></p>
            <p>Legaux's contractual relations with the Vine Company are documented in some detail in ntries for March 3-12, 1810. His intitial appointment as Superintendent is tipped into the inside cover of volume 1. Equally interesting are Legaux's dispute with Bernard McMahon (see August 7, 1813) regarding the sale of 3,000 vine cuttings.</p>
            <p>The last of the four volumes in the collection is a weather and farm diary maintained by Legaux after the failure of the Vine Company until his death in 1827. The journals were bequeathed to William J. Duane, politician and son of William Duane, however Duane records that Legaux's executor (and son-in-law), John Righter, failed to deliver the volume covering the period Aug. 1, 1814-July 31, 1822. Duane wrote that he "did not think it discreet to coerce."</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref5">
            <head>Arrangement note</head>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colname="col-0"/>
                        <colspec colname="col-1"/>
                        <colspec colname="col-2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> Volume I. Vine Company of Pennsylvania Records </entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> June 4, 1803-October 17, 1805 </entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> 194p. </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> Volume II. Vine Company of Pennsylvania Records </entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> October 18, 1805-August 12, 1809 </entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> 176p. </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> Volume III. Vine Company of Pennsylvania Records </entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> August 12, 1809-July 31, 1814 </entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> 196p. </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> Volume IV. Peter Legaux Journal </entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> August 1, 1822-March 31, 1827 </entry>
                                <entry valign="top" align="left"> 294p. </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table></p>
        </arrangement>
        <acqinfo id="ref7">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Gift of William J. Duane (to whom Legaux bequeathed it), 1866.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <prefercite id="ref8">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: Peter Legaux, Journal of the Vine Company of Pennsylvania, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <altformavail id="ref9">
            <head>Existence and Location of Copies note</head>
            <p>The journals have been microfilmed (Film 1467, reel 3).</p>
        </altformavail>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref10">
            <head>Related Archival Materials note</head>
            <p>The APS houses two sets of meteorological observations made by Legaux at Spring Mill:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                    <archref>Meteorological Observations, 1820-1821. 
                        <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> 551.5 L52</archref></item>
                <item>
                    <archref>Observations météorologiques faites à Springmill, 1787-1800. 
                        <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph> 551.5 M65</archref></item>
            </list>
            <p>In the Printed Materials Department are two important broadsides:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                    <bibref>
                        <title render="italic">Meteorological observations made at Springmill ...; Dec. 1787</title> (Philadelphia, 1788). 
                        <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 506.73Am4mc</bibref></item>
                <item>
                    <bibref>
                        <title render="italic">Meteorological observations made at Springmill ...; May 1789</title> (Philadelphia, 1789). 
                        <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>: 506.73Am4mc</bibref></item>
            </list>
        </relatedmaterial>
        <bibliography id="ref15">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <bibref>In October 1792 Legaux donated a copy of Moses Pereira de Leon, 
                <title render="italic">Essai Historique sur la Colonie de Surinam</title> (Paramaribo, 1788). 
                <emph render="bold">Call no.</emph>988 P41e</bibref>
        </bibliography>
        <odd id="ref24">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>This journal details Peter Legaux's attempt to create an American vineyard. The MOLE description contains a wealth of information about the journal, the vineyard's undertaking, and the APS's involvement with it.</p>
        </odd>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname source="ingest">McMahon, Bernard, ca.1760?-1816</persname>
            <corpname source="ingest">Vine Company of Pennsylvania.</corpname>
            <subject source="leah">Business and Skilled Trades</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">Business Records and Accounts</genreform>
            <subject source="ingest">Grapes</subject>
            <subject source="ingest">Meteorology--Pennsylvania--Observations</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Natural History</subject>
            <geogname source="ingest">Pennsylvania--Climate</geogname>
            <subject source="ingest">Viticulture--Pennsylvania</subject>
            <subject source="ingest">Weather</subject>
            <genreform source="ingest">Weather diaries</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref25" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Journal of the Vine Company of Pennsylvania</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid12876001" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">1-4</container>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>4.0 Volume(s)</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                    <unitdate>1803-1827</unitdate>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref16" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Volume I. Vine Company of Pennsylvania Records</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114924" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">1</container>
                        <unitdate>June 4, 1803-October 17, 1805</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref17" label="General Physical Description note">194p.</physdesc>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Volume II. Vine Company of Pennsylvania Records</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114923" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">2</container>
                        <unitdate>October 18, 1805-August 12, 1809</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref19" label="General Physical Description note">176p.</physdesc>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Volume III. Vine Company of Pennsylvania Records</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114922" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">3</container>
                        <unitdate>August 12, 1809-July 31, 1814</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref21" label="General Physical Description note">196p.</physdesc>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref22" level="otherlevel">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Volume IV. Peter Legaux Journal</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid114921" type="Volume" label="Mixed materials">4</container>
                        <unitdate>August 1, 1822-March 31, 1827</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref23" label="General Physical Description note">294p.</physdesc>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
