<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.B63-ead.xml">bohlen.xml</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>John Bohlen Collection
                    <date type="span">1808-1865</date>
                    <num>Mss.B.B63</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by rsc</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
                <date>2002</date>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T18:54-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>ENG</langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>John Bohlen Collection</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.B63</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>0.25 Linear feet</extent>
                <extent>10 items</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1889/1912" type="inclusive">1889-1912</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref1" label="Abstract">Born in Schiffdorf (near Bremerhafen), John Bohlen became one of Philadelphia's most prominent merchants at the turn of the nineteenth century. Running a profitable concern in partnership with his brother Bohl (1754-1836), John Bohlen imported commodities from their native Holland. Thanks to an insatiable American thirst for gin, Bohlen amassed an immense fortune that enabled him to travel in the same social circles as Stephen Girard and others among the mercantile elite and to win a spot in 1816 as one of the Directors of the Bank of the United States. By the time of his death, he was one of only eleven Philadelphians whose personal estates exceeded one million dollars in value. 
                <lb/>The Bohlen Collection contains a scant ten letters that appear to have been retained, as much as anything, for their autograph interest. Although they shed relatively little light on the life of John Bohlen, they do offer interesting glimpses into the personalities of Bohlen's famous correspondents, including Stephen Girard, Francis Scott Key, Meriwether Lewis, Virgil Maxcy, Oliver Hazard Perry, and Timothy Pickering.</abstract>
            <physloc id="ref47" label="Paging">LH-MV-C-2</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Bohlen, John</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd id="ref45">
            <head>Naval History Note</head>
            <p>The Bohlen Collection contains one item which may be of interest to naval historians:</p>
            <p>
                <ref target="ref27">Perry, Oliver Hazard</ref>. Letter to Daniel Murray. 1818 March 1. "In reply to your inquiry respecting the affair which has...lately made so much noise, and which has brought upon me such a torrent of abuse and malignant calumny -- I shall only briefly state that [the circumstances as related] are all false with the exception of my having given personal chastisement to an impertinent and insolent fellow, -- who is destitute of truth and spirit -- and who has been base enough to circulate the most unfounded slander, and then deny it under his own hand." 1 item.</p>
        </odd>
        <odd id="ref46">
            <head>Early American History Note</head>
            <p>John Bohlen was a prominent Philadelphia merchant in the nineteenth century, dying a millionaire. Bohlen, a Hollander, established a firm with his brother that specialized in trade with his native country. His greatest success came in the lucrative gin trade. As his business increased, so too did his connections. He served on the Board of the first Bank of the United States and was well-connected with highest the political and business leaders in the nation. Although John Bohlen was a prominent and successful businessman, these documents have little bearing on Bohlen himself. Instead, they are a series of letters (ten total) written by prominent Americans either to Bohlen or to his relatives.</p>
            <p>The collection seems to have been passed down through the family. Although the content rarely sheds much life on the Bohlen’s life or career, the letters offer some hint into the social circles that Bohlen operated within. Letters from Meriwether Lewis, Stephen Girard, and the Bank of the United States to Bohlen touch on financial matters. Other letters are often notes of acknowledgement or an exchange of pleasantries. The letter from Francis Scott Key to Daniel Murray discusses a sermon and includes an extract from it.</p>
        </odd>
        <processinfo id="ref13">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>Catalogued rsc, 2002.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <acqinfo id="ref11">
            <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition note</head>
            <p>Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Francis H. Bohlen, 1999.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <prefercite id="ref9">
            <head>Preferred Citation note</head>
            <p>Cite as: John Bohlen Collection, American Philosophical Society.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <scopecontent id="ref5">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The Bohlen Collection contains a scant ten letters that appear to have been retained, as much as anything, for their autograph interest. Although they shed relatively little light on the life of John Bohlen, they do offer interesting glimpses into the personalities of Bohlen's famous correspondents. Five letters were received by Bohlen, three letters by his relative by marriage, Daniel Murray, and one each by other relatives, Elizabeth Dorsey and John Gregg.</p>
            <p>Among the interesting items in the collection is a fine letter written by Meriwether Lewis in Saint Louis, 1808, regarding collecting debts owed to Bohlen, a letter of Timothy Pickering to Elizabeth Dorsey displaying his eloquent and gracious style, waxing over his visit to her home, and a prototypical Oliver Hazard Perry letter fulminating about calumnies made against him. The three page letter of Francis Scott Key is also interesting in that it includes two pages of excerpts from a sermon that impressed Key.</p>
            <p>Also included in the collection are a letter apprising Bohlen of his appointment as Director of the Bank of the U.S., and two letters of one of Bohlen's relatives pertaining to an early (1850s and 1860s) interest in collecting the autographs of famous Americans and mentioning the discovery of an account book of George Washington's secreted in a wall at West Point.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist id="ref3">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>Born in Schiffdorf (near Bremerhafen), John Bohlen became one of Philadelphia's most prominent merchants at the turn of the nineteenth century, running a profitable concern in partnership with his brother Bohl (1754-1836) importing commodities from their native Holland. Thanks to an insatiable American thirst for gin, Bohlen amassed an immense fortune that enabled him to travel in the same social circles as Stephen Girard and others among the mercantile elite and to win a spot in 1816 as one of the Directors of the Bank of the United States. By the time of his death, he was one of only eleven Philadelphians whose personal estates exceeded one million dollars in value.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <controlaccess>
            <corpname source="ingest">Bank of the United States</corpname>
            <persname source="ingest">Calhoun, John B.</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Cole, J.</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Dorsey, Elizabeth</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Girard, Stephen, 1750-1831</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Maxcy, Virgil, 1785-1844</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Murray, Daniel</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Perry, Oliver Hazard, 1785-1819</persname>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829</persname>
            <persname source="ingest">Stone, John S.</persname>
            <subject source="leah">Business and Skilled Trades</subject>
            <genreform source="leah">General Correspondence</genreform>
            <subject source="leah">International Trade.</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Philadelphia History</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Religion</subject>
            <subject source="leah">Trade</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref14" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>John Bohlen Collection</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid4252" type="Box" label="Mixed materials">1</container>
                    <unitdate>1808-1865</unitdate>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref15" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to John Bohlen</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1808 December 24</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref17">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Re: debts owed Bohlen by Robert Westcott and James McGuffin, which Lewis will help recover.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to John Bohlen</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1810 January 1</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Girard, Stephen, 1750-1831</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref20">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Has been awarded $36,741 in the case Girard v. Biddle.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>LS to John Bohlen</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1816 November 1</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Bank of the U.S. Commissioners</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref23">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Notice of election as Director of the Bake of the U.S. Signed by W. Jones, Stephen Girard, Thomas William, Thomas Leiper, and Cadwalader Evans.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref24" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to Elizabeth Dorsey</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1816 December 29</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref26">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Gratified by his visit to West River, the polite society and chaste manners.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to Daniel Murray</unittitle>
                        <unitdate>1818 March 1</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Perry, Oliver Hazard, 1785-1819</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref29">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Re: state of Mrs. Blakely's pecuniary affairs.</p>
                        <p>"In reply to your inquiry respecting the affair which has lately made so much noice, and which had lately made so much noise, and which has brought upon me such a torrent of abuse and malignant calumny -- I shall only briefly state that they (the circumstances as related) are all false with the exception of my having given personal chastisement to an impertinent and insolent fellow, -- who is destitute of truth and spirit -- and who has been base enough to circulate the most unfounded slander, and then deny it under his own hand."</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to Daniel Murray</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1818 March 24</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Maxcy, Virgil, 1785-1844</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref32">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Thanks for the pamphlets.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref33" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to Daniel Murray</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>3p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1820 August 4</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref35">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Sending extract of a sermon he had mentioned</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref36" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to John Gregg</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>1p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1851 March 24</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Stone, John S.</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref38">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Letter of introduction for John Bohlen.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref39" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to John Bohlen</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>6p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1855 January 1</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Cole, J.</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref41">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Sending autographs of Washington (a page of an account book found at West Point), Marshall, and Madison.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref42" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ALS to John Bohlen</unittitle>
                        <physdesc>
                            <extent>2p.</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                        <unitdate>1865 Nov. 29</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Calhoun, John B.</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref44">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Sending autographs of the Lincolns.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
