<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ead xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <eadheader repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-PPAmP" url="http://www.amphilsoc.org/mole/view?docId=ead/Mss.B.C694-ead.xml"></eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>
                    <num>Mss.B.C694</num>
                    <num>Mss.B.C694</num>
                </titleproper>
                <author>Finding aid prepared by Finding aid prepared by Anne Harney</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addressline>105 South Fifth Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>Philadelphia, PA, 19106</addressline>
                    <addressline>215-440-3400</addressline>
                    <addressline>manuscripts@amphilsoc.org</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2013-09-13T19:03-0400</date>
            </creation>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unittitle>Frank Shipley Collins papers, 1872-1919</unittitle>
            <unitid>Mss.B.C694</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>American Philosophical Society</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="eng"/>
            </langmaterial>
            <container id="cid13016003" type="Box" label="Manuscripts">1-5</container>
            <physdesc>
                <extent>2.5 Linear feet</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate normal="1872/1919" type="inclusive">1872-1919</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">Contains letters and copies of letters on botanical subjects, principally algae, many on the identification of species and on the sale and exchange of mounted specimens. 18 items refer to the United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842).</abstract>
            <physdesc id="ref1" label="General Physical Description note">
                <extent>1,800 items.</extent></physdesc>
            <physdesc id="ref3" label="General Physical Description note">Ca. 1800 items, 2.5 linear ft.</physdesc>
            <physloc id="ref64" label="Paging">LH-B-15-9; LH-MV-E-1 (B C694.a)</physloc>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Boruet, E.</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Bosse, A. Weber von.</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Clarke, Cora Huidekoper, b. 1851</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest" role="Author (aut)">Collins, Frank S., (Frank Shipley), 1848-1920</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Crozier, William John, 1892-1955</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Davis, Bradley M., (Bradley Moore), b. 1871</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Gillette, Lucy F.</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Grover, Frederick Orville, 1868-</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Hauck, Ferdinand, 1845-1889</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Haven, Tracy E.</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Hoyt, William Deans</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Humphrey, James Ellis, 1861-1897</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">K. Yendo, (Kichisaburo), 1874-1921</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Kolderup Rosenvinge, L., (Lauritz), 1858-1939</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Reinbold, Theodor, 1840-1892</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Richards, Herbert M., (Herbert Maule), 1871-1928</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Robinson, Benjamin Lincoln, 1864-1935</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Saunders, De Alton, 1870-</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Sauvageau, C., (Camille), 1861-1936</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Schramm, Jacob R., (Jacob Richard), b. 1885</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Schuh, Richard Edwin, b. 1860</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Terry, William A.</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Traill, George W.</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Transeau, Edgar Nelson, 1875-1960</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">West, G. S., (George Stephen), 1876-1919</persname>
            </origination>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="ingest">Wille, N., (Nordal), 1858-1924</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <bioghist id="ref4">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>The botanist Frank Shipley Collins (1848-1920) was an authority on American algae. He spent his life in Massachusetts where he worked for the Malden Rubber Shoe Company for over three decades. Despite the fact that Collins’ formal education never extended beyond high school, he became a noted phycologist with a particular interest in New England algae. He is generally considered the foremost American algologist of his time.</p>
            <p>Frank Shipley Collins was born in 1848 in Boston, the son of Joshua Cobb Collins and Elizabeth Ann Carter Collins. As a young boy he preferred books and the instructive stories of two aunts, who were teachers, to outdoor play. He was introduced to modern and ancient languages as well as mathematics and botany at an early age. He subsequently enrolled at a private school in Malden, and, after the death of his father, attended public schools in that town. He continued his home studies of Greek, Latin, French, mathematics, and astronomy, and at age sixteen graduated from high school. A severe case of asthma kept him from most activities, and he spent the next couple of years at home, focusing on the study of music and art. In 1873 he spent seven months in Europe, much of which he devoted to activities related to music and art.</p>
            <p>His mother and aunts hoped that young Frank would attend Harvard University but his grandfather decided that work would be a better choice. Collins evidently tried his hands in different trades until he settled on bookkeeping. He eventually found employment with the Malden Rubber Shoe Company as a ticket clerk. He also worked on improving the methods by which the shoes were made. He quickly rose to the rank of manager and remained with the company for over thirty years; even after his retirement in 1913 he returned to the company as an efficiency expert during WWI.</p>
            <p>While Collins’s formal education never extended beyond high school, he displayed a keen interest in a range of subjects, including art and music, Spanish, and, for a time, theosophy, a field in which he subsequently published an essay. He also devoted considerable time to scientific endeavors, especially botany. As early as the 1870s he seems to have been associated with George Edward Davenport (1833-1907) and Lorin Low Dame (1838-1903) in the activities of the Middlesex Scientific Field Club, later the Middlesex Institute, which was founded in 1878. He was elected vice-president in 1878, and he delivered a paper before the club in 1879.</p>
            <p>In 1875 Collins married Anna Lendrum Holmes. Shortly thereafter he became interested in algae when during a visit to the sea shore he saw cards with sea mosses for sale to tourists. Collins was fascinated by the cards, partly because he recognized right away that the naming was quite inadequate. He set out to correct the botanical names and to examine algae more carefully. At that time little was known about American species of algae, especially local environments, and the existing literature tended to be incomplete and unreliable. Collins began to explore New England’s coast in search of algae, and he soon acquire an understanding of marine flora that was unrivaled. By the late 1870s Collins was speaking on the subject, and in 1879 he announced in 
                <emph render="italic">The Naturalist</emph> that he was actively seeking to exchange New England algae with specimens from other parts of the country, especially Florida and California. Several collectors in these regions responded by sending speciments to him. By 1882 he published the first in a series of “Notes” on New England algae in the 
                <emph render="italic">Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club</emph>. He subsequently extended his work from biodiversity assessments with a regional focus on New England to include studies of marine flora along the Atlantic coast to Jamaica and Bermuda, which he visited several times.</p>
            <p>In 1888 Dame and Collins published their “Flora of Middlesex County, Massachusetts” under the auspices of the Middlesex Institute. Over the following years Collins published several essays on algae, culminating in his most important publication, his book 
                <emph render="italic">The Green Algae of North America</emph> (1918). In addition, with the botanist William A. Setchell (1864-1943) and his fellow businessman and amateur botanist Issac Holden (1832-1903), Collins compiled the 
                <emph render="italic">Phycotheca Boreali-Americana</emph> (1912-1917), a published set of dried North American algae that required the handling of over 200,000 specimens. With the help of collectors and students, Collins undertook much of the work required for the completion of the fascicles, including not only the assembling, sorting, labeling, and design, but also the necessary financial details. From 1895 to 1919, the collection was issued in forty-six bound volumes and five elephant folio volumes.</p>
            <p>Collins assembled one of the finest marine herbaria of his time. He donated specimens of New England algae to the Boston Society of Natural History and to the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia. He also completely rearranged the algae in the collections of the Boston Society of Natural History, Missouri Botanical Garden, and Harvard University. Collins’ own collections of algae survive in museums and universities across the country, including the New York Botanical Garden.</p>
            <p>Despite the fact that Collins lacked a college education and spent much of his time with business pursuits, his accomplishments in botany and especially phycology earned him the respect of the highest authorities in the field. His correspondents included Eduoard Bornet (1828-1911), Ferdinand Hauck (1845-1889), George W. Traill (1836-1897), and Anna Weber-van Bosse (1852-1942). Collins was a member of the biological stations at Woods Hole, Masachusetts, and South Harpswell, Maine. He was also a member of the Middlesex Institute, the Boston Society of Natural History, the Massachusetts Horticultural Society (1913), American Society of Naturalists (1918), and the New England Botanical Club, whose journal 
                <emph render="italic">Rhodora</emph> he co-edited for several years and of which he was president from 1902 to 1905. He was corresponding member of the Torrey Botanical Club and a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences (1901). Tufts College awarded him an honorary master’s degree in 1910, and Harvard made him an associate in its museum. Collins died in New Haven, Connecticut, in 1920.</p>
            <p></p>
        </bioghist>
        <processinfo id="ref63">
            <head>Processing Information note</head>
            <p>The index contains only correspondence from a subset of the collection (B C694.1) concerning the Wilkes Exploration Expedition.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <controlaccess>
            <corpname source="ingest">United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842).</corpname>
            <subject source="lcsh">Algae.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Biological specimens -- Identification.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Botany -- Classification.</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Plants - Identification</subject>
            <genreform source="lcsh">Specimens.</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc>
            <c01 id="ref6" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Papers</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref7" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Collins, Malden, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Aug.29, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref8" label="General Physical Description note">10x8</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Library of Congress</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref9">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Washington, Typed L.S.: J.L. Farnum. 1p. Enc. wanting. Sends information concerning publications of the Wilkes exploring expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref10" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Walter Deane, Cambridge, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Nov. 7, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref11" label="General Physical Description note">10-1/2x8</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Fisher, A. K. (Albert Kenrick), 1856-1948</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref12">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Washington, Typed L. 2p. Mutilated. Concerning T.R. Peale's publication of the Wilkes expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref13" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Hollins [sic]</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Nov. 15, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref14" label="General Physical Description note">8x5-1/4</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Thayer, John Eliot, 1862-</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref15">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Lancaster, Mass., A.L.S. 1p. Cannot help him since he never heard of the report [published after the Wilkes expedition?].</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref16" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Collins</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Nov. 23, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref17" label="General Physical Description note">8-3/4x5-3/4</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Deane, Ruthven, 1851-1934</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref18">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>A.L.S. 2p. Forwards his inquiry. For answer, see: Academy of natural science of Philadelphia to F.S. Collins; Nov.24, 1911.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to F[rank] S. Collins</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Nov. 24, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref20" label="General Physical Description note">11x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref21">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning T.R. Peale's publication of results of Wilkes exploration expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref22" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to F[rank] S. Collins</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Nov. 27, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref23" label="General Physical Description note">8-1/2x5-1/4</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">American Academy of Arts and Sciences.</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref24">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Boston, A.L.S.: Mrs. A.H. Holden. 1p. Lists volumes of the Wilkes expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref25" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to F[rank] S. Collins, Malden, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Nov. 27, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref26" label="General Physical Description note">11x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">New York Botanical Garden</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref27">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>New York, Typed L.S.: Marshall A. Howe. 2p. Concerning Sullivant's publication of mosses from the Wilkes expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref28" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Collins, Malden, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Dec. 1, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref29" label="General Physical Description note">10x8</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Library of Congress</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref30">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Washington, Typed L.S.: H.H.B. Meyer. 1p. Lists publication of T.R. Peale and Sullivant from the Wilkes expedition. Enclosed Originally in letter from Library of Congress to Collins; Dec. 1, 1911.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref31" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to [Frank S.] Collins</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Dec. 1, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref32" label="General Physical Description note">5-1/2x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Preston, Howard W. (Howard Willis), b. 1859</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref33">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Providence, R.I., A.L.S. 1p. Will check on the library in question.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref34" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to [Frank S. Collins]</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Dec. 2, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref35" label="General Physical Description note">11x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">C , J F</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref36">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Providence, R.I., Typed L.S. with initials. 1p. His knowledge of the Wilkes expedition publications.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref37" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Collins, Malden, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Dec. 4, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref38" label="General Physical Description note">10x8</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Library of Congress</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref39">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Washington, Typed L.S.: J.L. Farnum. 1p. Enc. Encloses answer to his request. For enclosure, see: Library of Congress to F.S. Collins; Dec. 1, 1911.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref40" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to F[rank] S.Collins, Malden, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Dec. 5, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref41" label="General Physical Description note">11x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Preston, Howard W. (Howard Willis), b. 1859</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref42">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Providence, R.I., Typed L.S. 1p. Cites location of publications of the Wilkes expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref43" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to [Frank S. Collins]</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Dec. 19, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref44" label="General Physical Description note">9-1/4x5-3/4</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Faxon, Charles Edward, 1846-1918</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref45">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>A.L.S. 2p. Concerning publications of the Wilkes expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref46" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Collins</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Dec. 21, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref47" label="General Physical Description note">10x8</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">New York State Library</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref48">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Albany, N.Y., A.L.S.: Frank L. Tolman. 1p. Cannot answer his question since fire has destroyed their records.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref49" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Collins, Malden, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Dec. 30, 1911</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref50" label="General Physical Description note">11x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">New York Public Library</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref51">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>New York, Typed L.S.: H.M. Lydenberg. 2p. Lists publication of the Wilkes expedition, recently acquired.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref52" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Papers</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>1911-1912</unitdate>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Collins, Frank S. (Frank Shipley), 1848-1920</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref53">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>D. 18 items. Various sizes. Concerning the Wilkes Exploration Expedition. Table of contents available.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref54" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to [Frank S.] Collins</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Jan. 3, 1912</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref55" label="General Physical Description note">11x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref56">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>Philadelphia, A.L.S. : Witmer Stone. Lists holdings of the Wilkes expedition publications.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref57" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Collins, Malden, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Jan. 3, 1912</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref58" label="General Physical Description note">11x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">New York Public Library</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref59">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>New York, Typed L.S.: Wilberforce Eames. 1p. Hopes to publish an account of the publications of the Wilkes expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref60" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Letter to Frank S. Collins, Malden, Massachusetts</unittitle>
                        <unitid>B C694.1</unitid>
                        <unitdate>Jan. 6, 1912</unitdate>
                        <physdesc id="ref61" label="General Physical Description note">11x8-1/2</physdesc>
                        <origination label="creator">
                            <persname source="ingest">Minnesota State Library</persname>
                        </origination>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref62">
                        <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
                        <p>St. Paul, Minnesota, Typed L.S.: Elias J. Lien. 1p. Has no publications of the Wilkes expedition.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref65" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Algal scrapbooks</unittitle>
                    <unitid>B C694.a</unitid>
                    <container id="cid13282004" type="Volume" label="Manuscripts">1-4</container>
                    <physdesc>
                        <extent>4.0 vols.</extent>
                    </physdesc>
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
